<resources>
    <string name="app_name">Monumental Final Version</string>

    <string-array name="world_wonders">
        <item>Alhambra</item>
        <item>Angkor Wat</item>
        <item>Big Ben</item>
        <item>Bolshoi Theatre</item>
        <item>Borobudur</item>
        <item>Brandenburg Gate</item>
        <item>Broadway</item>
        <item>Casa de Contratación</item>
        <item>Chichen Itza</item>
        <item>The Colosseum</item>
        <item>Christo Redentor</item>
        <item>Eiffel Tower</item>
        <item>Forbidden City</item>
        <item>Golden Gate Bridge</item>
        <item>The Great Wall</item>
        <item>Hagia Sophia</item>
        <item>Hermitage</item>
        <item>Kotoku-In</item>
        <item>The Louvre</item>
        <item>Machu Picchu</item>
        <item>Mahabodhi Temple</item>
        <item>Meenakshi Temple</item>
        <item>Mont. St. Michel</item>
        <item>Notre Dame</item>
        <item>Országház</item>
        <item>The Parthenon</item>
        <item>Petra</item>
        <item>Poatala Palace</item>
        <item>The Pyramids</item>
        <item>St. Basil Cathedral</item>
        <item>Statue of Liberty</item>
        <item>Stonehenge</item>
        <item>Sydney Opera House</item>
        <item>Taj Mahal</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="world_wonders_quote">
        <item>\"Everything here appears calculated to inspire kind and happy feelings, for everything is delicate and beautiful\" \n\n -Washington Irving</item>
        <item>\"The temple is like no other building in the world. It has towers and decoration and all the refinements which the human genius can conceive of.\" \n\n– Antonio da Magdalena </item>
        <item>\"Don’t watch the big clock; do what it does. Keep going.\" \n\n– Sam Levenson</item>
        <item>\"Bolshoi Ballet is a universe of the imagination, a place of magic and enchantment, beauty and romance. Its many worlds vibrate with graceful dancers, glorious music, and sumptuous costumes.\" \n\n– Trudy Garfunkel</item>
        <item>\"When you realize how perfect everything is, you will tilt your head back and laugh at the sky.\" \n\n– Gautama Buddha</item>
        <item>\"Pale Death beats equally at the poor man\'s gate and at the palaces of kings.\" \n\n – Horace</item>
        <item>\"Broadway is a main artery of New York cultural life - the hardened artery.\" \n\n– Walter Winchell</item>
        <item>\"All other lands found on the western side of the boundary shall belong to the King and Queen of Castille—and their successors.\" \n\n– Treaty of Tordesillas </item>
        <item>\"The katun is established at Chichen Itza. The settlement of the Itza shall take place there. The quetzal shall come, the green bird shall come. Ah Kantenal shall come. It is the word of God. The Itza shall come.\" \n\n– The Books of Chilam Balam</item>
        <item>\"While the Colosseum stands, Rome shall stand; when the Colosseum falls, Rome shall fall; when Rome falls, the world shall fall.\" \n\n – Saint Bede</item>
        <item>\"Thus, the sculpture serves to give people one thought - Everything is in God\'s hands.\" \n\n– Sergey Semenov</item>
        <item>\"We live only to discover beauty, all else is a form of waiting\" \n\n– Kahlil Gibran</item>
        <item>\"Most of us can, as we choose, make of this world either a palace or a prison.\" \n\n – John Lubbock</item>
        <item>\"The Golden Gate of Sleep unbar \nWhere Strength and Beauty, met together,\nKindle their image like a star\nIn a sea of glassy weather!\" \n\n– Percy Bysshe Shelley</item>
        <item>\"The art of war teaches us to rely not on the likelihood of the enemy\'s not attacking, but rather on the fact that we have made our position unassailable.\" \n\n – Sun Tzu</item>
        <item>\"For it soars to a height to match the sky, and as if surging up from among the other buildings it stands on high and looks down upon the remainder of the city, adorning it, because it is a part of it, but glorying in its own beauty.\" \n\n– Procopius, De Aedificis </item>
        <item>\"Museums are on the front lines of the fight for culture, of good with evil - in any case, of the fight against platitudes and primitiveness.\" \n\n – Mikhail Piotrovsky, Director of the State Hermitage</item>
        <item>\"O ye who tread the Narrow Way, by Tophet-flare to Judgment Day, be gentle when \‘the heathen\’ pray, to Buddha at Kamakura!\" \n\n – Rudyard Kipling</item>
        <item>\"Every genuine work of art has as much reason for being as the earth and the sun.\" \n\n– Ralph Waldo Emerson</item>
        <item>\"Few romances can ever surpass that of the granite citadel on top of the beetling precipices of Machu Picchu, the crown of Inca Land.\" \n\n– Hiram Bingham</item>
        <item>\"In a dusty, bustling corner of the Indian state of Bihar, there is a magical place that one might think of as the hub of Buddhism.\" \n\n- Visitor\'s Guide, Bodh Gaya</item>
        <item>\"We greet you, Devi Meenakshi, she who shines like a thousand-million suns, adorned with bracelets and garlands... She who is auspicious, she who embodies existence. I always bow to you, whose compassion is an ocean.\" \n\n– Adi Shankara</item>
        <item>\"Church and State, Soul and Body, God and Man, are all one at Mont Saint Michel, and the business of all is to fight, each in his own way, or to stand guard for each other.\" \n\n – Henry Adams</item>
        <item>\"Architecture has recorded the great ideas of the human race. Not only every religious symbol, but every human thought has its page in that vast book.\" \n\n- Victor Hugo </item>
        <item>\"With self-government is freedom, and with freedom is justice and patriotism.\" \n\n – Lajos Kossuth</item>
        <item>\"Earth proudly wears the Parthenon as the best gem upon her zone.\" \n\n– Ralph Waldo Emerson </item>
        <item>\"Match me with such marvels, save in Eastern clime, A rose-red city half as old as time!\" \n\n– John Burgon"</item>
        <item>\"The first time I stepped onto the rooftop of the Potala Palace, I felt, as never before or since, as if I were stepping onto the rooftop of my being: onto some dimension of consciousness that I’d never visited before.\" \n\n– Pico Iyer</item>
        <item>\"From the heights of these pyramids, forty centuries look down on us.\" \n\n– Napoleon Bonaparte </item>
        <item>\"One had a twisted design, red, on a green ground; another, all prickly angles, yellow and black; a third was ornamented with scales of blue and crimson; a [fourth] was in quarters like a melon.\" \n\n – Katharine Blanche Guthrie</item>
        <item>\"Give me your tired, your poor, your huddled masses yearning to breathe free, the wretched refuse of your teeming shore. Send these, the homeless, tempest-tossed to me, I lift my lamp beside the golden door!\" \n\n– Emma Lazarus
 </item>
        <item>\"Time crumbles things; everything grows old and is forgotten under the power of time\" \n\n– Aristotle
 </item>
        <item>\"An opera begins long before the curtain goes up and ends long after it has come down. It starts in my imagination, it becomes my life, and it stays part of my life long after I\'ve left the opera house.\" \n\n– Maria Callas </item>
        <item>\"The Taj Mahal rises above the banks of the river like a solitary tear suspended on the cheek of time.\" \n\n– Rabindranath Tagore </item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="world_wonders_desc">
        <item>Found in southern Spain, the Alhambra is a large palace complex of the Nasrid Dynasty, who controlled the region in the mid 14th century. Construction began sometime around 1238 AD under the rule of Ibn al-Hamar, and continued under his successors. Taking its name from the red hue of its walls, the name Alhambra is translated as the \"Red Fortress\". It integrated the natural beauty of the spot, with structures and gardens designed and outfitted by the finest Muslim, Jewish and even Christian craftsmen and artisans of the region.</item>
        <item>It has stood for nearly 1,000 years, a monument to a god and possibly the final resting place of the conqueror king who built it.\n\nAnd still, the temple at Angkor Wat endures, its central tower rising 213 feet above the surrounding jungle. Constructed by the Khmer King Suryavarman II in the Twelfth century in what is now northern Cambodia, it is one of the world\'s tallest religious monuments.\n\nA pilgrim to the city-temple of the Hindu God Vishnu would first cross a 650-foot wide and 14-feet deep moat surrounding the structure before entering a \'gopura,\' a three-towered entrance leading to a raised walkway. Inside the temple complex proper, they would find four smaller towers surrounding one central 213-foot tower, evoking the sacred Mount Meru.\n\nKhmer Shaivist temples typically face east, but because Angkor Wat faces west, the final resting place for Suryavarman\'s remains would be a temple honoring Vishnu.</item>
        <item>\The giant bell, Big Ben, is housed in the Elizabeth Tower – so named to celebrate the Diamond Jubilee of Queen Elizabeth II (being just the “Clock Tower” before that) – at the north end of the Palace of Westminster, where sits the Houses of Parliament. Being rather casual in language, most Brits and flocks of tourists tend to refer to the whole thing as “Big Ben.” The great 16-ton bell was cast in August 1856 at the foundry at Stockton-on-Tees and recast at the Whitechapel Bell Foundry in April 1858 after it cracked while being transported to London. The pendulum clockwork was designed by the Astronomer Royal and crafted by the clockmaker Edward Dent and his stepson Frederick; it was ready in 1854. So fine is the precision, that adding or removing a penny (English, of course) to the pendulum will change the speed by four-tenths of a second each day. But all had to await the completion of the clock tower itself, which wasn’t done until 1859. Despite being silenced during wartime and the occasional breakdown, Big Ben has chimed the hour ever since.\</item>
        <item>\The Imperial Bolshoi Theatre of Moscow – bolshoi being the Russian for “grand” – is home for the Bolshoi Ballet and Bolshoi Opera companies, among the oldest and largest in the world (the ballet has some 200 dancers). The ballet company was founded in March 1776 by Prince Urusov and Michael Maddox, a British theater manager; after performing in private homes for some years, the company was profitable enough to acquire the Petrovka Theater and opened there for the first time in December 1780. Sadly, the Petrovka burned down in 1805, to be replaced by the New Arbat Theater, which burned down in 1812 during Napoleon’s occupation of the city.\n\nThe current Bolshoi Theater was built between 1821 and 1824, and it managed not to burn down – although it was renovated in 1843, 1856, 1921, 2002 and 2011. The last renovation included restoring the theater’s acoustics to the original high quality (which had been mucked up by the Soviets) and restoring the original imperial décor (which had been ripped out by those same Soviets).\</item>
        <item>\Borobudur is a Buddhist candi in Magelang, Java, consisting of six square platforms surmounted by three circular platforms, atop which are 72 small stupas surrounding a large central stupa. The structure is decorated with 2672 bas-relief carvings and 504 Buddhist statues. The temple\'s three levels represent the three realms of Buddhist cosmology: the world of desires, the world of forms, and the formless world. Construction of Borobudur was completed at some point between 778 and 850 AD, during the Sailendra dynasty. Around 1006 the nearby capital of the successor Medang Kingdom was abandoned due to a series of volcanic eruptions; pilgrimages to Borobudur ceased shortly thereafter. The temple was lost for centuries under layers of ash and jungle until discovered by the British lieutenant governor of Java, Sir Stamford Raffles, in 1814.\</item>
        <item>\The Brandenburg Gate is the only surviving town gate of the city of Berlin. A beautiful "triumphal arch" constructed in the Greek style in 1788-91, it features many columns and is surmounted by the "Quadriga of Victory," a statue of a chariot drawn by four horses. It stands at the end of the avenue Unter den Linden.\n\nAfter World War II, Berlin was partitioned between sections controlled by the Soviet Union, and the United States and its allies. The Berlin Wall was constructed by the Soviets to keep the two parts of the city separated. The Brandenburg Gate was in a sort of a "no-man\'s land" between the two factions, and from 1961-1989 neither side had access. The Gate was reopened in 1989 as part of the reunification of Berlin and Germany.\n\nToday it stands as a proud symbol of the reunified city and country, and it is visited by tens of thousands of tourists from both east and west.\</item>
        <item>\Broadway is a 15-mile long thoroughfare through the heart of Manhattan and the Bronx in New York City, lined with offices, shops and apartments … but no-one thinks of those. Instead, Broadway is best known for the middle section between 42nd and 53rd Streets dubbed the “Great White Way” – the Theater District. Commencing in the mid-1800s a number of theaters opened on Broadway. In 1880 AD a stretch between Madison and Union squares was illuminated with arc lamps, making it one of the first electrically lit streets in the United States (leave it to New Yorkers to light up theaters before homes, hospitals and schools). Spurred by growing American wealth and cultural aspirations, the theaters made it a mecca of popular entertainment. By 1900 some 20 theaters had opened along this stretch, and so bright were their electric billboards that it became the Great White Way. In 1925 at its peak popularity, there were 80 theaters along Broadway, specializing in lavish productions, primarily revues and musicals.\</item>
        <item>\When Spain joined the late 15th Century’s exploration race, Queen Isabella I of Castile and Ferdinand II of Aragón realized they needed a firmer grasp on colonial trade and expansion. Through their Casa de Contratación, a “House of Trade” created to regulate trade and procurement, the Spanish crown controlled everything related to trade and sea travel down to the smallest details. Even their navigation and cartography school kept literal trade secrets in house.\n\nSeville was home to the first incarnation of the Casa de Contración, but the agency moved to Cádiz in 1717. Moving to a city near the southern tip of Spain streamlined the influx of ships, which had previously traveled up the highly trafficked Guadalquivir River. The Casa remained in Cádiz until its termination in 1790 due to the empire’s growing debts.\</item>
        <item>\Chichen Itza is an extraordinary city of stone built in the Yucatán, Mexico. Some of the oldest buildings and pyramids date back to 1500 years ago and are of Toltec and Mayan origin.\n\nChichen Itza consists of buildings, temples and courtyards of stone. A large "pok tap ok" or ceremonial ball court stands off to one side. (Ceremonial ball is that most interesting of games in which two sides sought to pass the ball through hoops at each end of the court. The captain of the winning team was then beheaded as a sacrifice to the gods.) Though the city is much ravaged by time (and looters), there still remain many beautiful stone carvings and statues.\n\nAt the center of the city stands the mighty stepped pyramid of Kukulcan, also known as "El Castillo." Constructed around the 13th century, El Castillo is approximately 17 meters square (180 feet square) at the base and 24 m (78 feet) in height. As was the Mayan practice, Kukulcan was constructed atop an older and smaller pyramid.\n\nChichen Itza was a thriving city until the 13th century, when revolt and civil war broke out among the Mayans, at which point the city went into a steep decline from which it never recovered. The center of the city was largely abandoned and in ruins by the time of the Spanish Conquest of the Yucatán in the 16th century.\</item>
        <item>\The Flavian Amphitheater, better known as the “Coliseum” lies in the center of Rome. Construction began during the reign of Emperor Vespasian, c. 72 AD, funded by the spoils from the Jewish Second Temple after the fall of Jerusalem during the First Jewish-Roman War. Built of concrete and stone, it is the largest amphitheater ever built, and one of the great wonders of ancient architecture and engineering. It could hold between 50 and 80 thousand spectators to watch gladiatorial matches, animal hunts, mass executions, and more.\n\nBy the time medieval Christianity had taken root, it had been repurposed to house low-rent apartments, workshops, quarters for a religious order, a quarry and a Christian shrine. Although knocked about by earthquakes and pillaged by stone-robbers, the Coliseum is still pretty impressive two millennia after the inaugural gladiatorial slaughter.\</item>
        <item>\The largest art deco statue in the world, Cristo Redentor (“Christ the Redeemer”) stands atop Corcovado Mountain 2300 feet above Rio de Janeiro, keeping a watchful eye on the sinners of that city. With arms spread wide to embrace the city sprawling below in spectacular disorder, this statue of Christ stands 98 feet tall, with the arms measuring 92 feet from fingertip to fingertip. It was sculpted by the Frenchman Paul Landowski, and built of reinforced concrete and soapstone.\n\nThe idea of putting a giant statue of Christ above the city was first proposed by the Catholic priest Pedro Boss; proposed again in 1920 by the “Catholic Circle” of Rio, the group raised the necessary funds from donations, mostly from devout Brazilian Catholics (of course). Construction began in 1922, and the monument opened to the public in October 1931.\</item>
        <item>\The Eiffel Tower is one of the world\'s most famous landmarks. Built for the Universal Exposition of 1889, the tower rises 300 meters (984 feet) above Paris\' Champ de Mars, near the Seine River. Structural engineer Alexandre Gustave Eiffel built the tower to demonstrate how steel and iron could be utilized in the construction of extremely tall buildings. The cost was more than $1 million.\n\nThe tallest building in the world when it was originally completed, the Eiffel Tower drew crowds of awestruck observers from around the world. Today, it remains one of Paris\' leading tourist attractions.\</item>
        <item>\Lying in the center of Beijing, a visit to Gu Gong (the Imperial Palace of China) was forbidden to the common folk without special dispensation from the emperor himself; hence the complex became known across the land as the “Forbidden City” (much like most presidential residences these days).\n\nConstruction of the walled “city” – liberally sprinkled with ornamental gardens, graceful terraces, restful fountains and lots of utilitarian administrative offices – began in 1408 AD under the guidance of the Yonglu Emperor, third of the Ming dynasty.\n\nThe complex grew over the centuries, serving as home to 24 emperors of the Ming and Qing. It grew until it encompassed 9,999 rooms spread over 178 square acres, surrounded by a 170-foot wide moat and 32-foot high walls (just to make sure none of those commoners entered unchecked). At its peak, the Forbidden City was home to ten thousand people, all to serve the needs of one emperor.\</item>
        <item>\Nestled in the San Francisco fog is the iconic Golden Gate Bridge, a 1.7 mile long suspension bridge that defied everything believed to be true about engineering when it was completed in 1937. Spanning across the Golden Gate Strait, this wonder of the modern world connects San Francisco to northern California counties, providing a necessary commuter route and unnecessary traffic for residents and visitors alike.\n\nThough its name suggests the color of its beams, the bridge is actually painted International Orange. Although this wasn\'t the original intended color for the project – black and yellow stripes were the leading choice – it complemented the landscape and gave the bridge some much needed visibility in the fog. So much visibility that it is believed to be the most photographed bridge in the world, and has made its mark on pop culture in movies, television, and video games.\</item>
        <item>\The Great Wall of China is one of the largest and most famous man-made constructions in the entire world. Chinese rulers built the Great Wall to ward off attack from nomadic tribesmen living in modern Manchuria and Mongolia. Interestingly, the Great Wall was not designed to keep the nomads out - the Chinese knew it was all but impossible to defend such a long border - it was designed to make it difficult for the raiders to carry off loot, thus making raids far less profitable and thus less worth the risks involved.\n\nThere have actually been five different "Great Walls" built by different Chinese dynasties. The first four were constructed of earth and have since all but disappeared. The current wall was built almost entirely by the Ming Dynasty between 1368 and 1640 AD.\n\nThis wall was constructed on a grander scale, using more permanent materials (like stone). The Ming wall stretches for 6,354 km (3,948 miles) from Shanhai Pass on the Bohai Gulf in the east to Lop Nur in the southeast portion of Xinjiang\'s Uygur Autonomous Region in the west.This was the region where the Silk Road first entered China, and a series of watchtowers which could communicate via smoke signals were intended to pass messages rapidly along the wall\'s vast length.\</item>
        <item>\The Hagia Sophia, or "High Wisdom," was constructed in 530 AD as a Greek Orthodox church. It has been in service, most as a place of worship, for almost 1500 years. It is a remarkable building as it has survived many earthquakes, sometimes needing large repairs. It is a beautiful and ornate structure, built of stone and marble, and topped by a golden dome measuring over 30 m (100 feet) in diameter. An extremely difficult engineering challenge for the time, the dome has collapsed several times during its existence. Later on the Ottomans added 4 minarets, marking it one of the important mosques of the world.\n\nThe classical interior of the Hagia Sophia is a marvelous space of columns and arches extending up to the dome, which appears almost to float atop the building. It breathes the classical age, nowhere else left to be found. The interior was sheathed in colored marble and golden mosaics depicting biblical scenes and images of Christian saints.\n\nIn 1453 Constantinople was captured by the Ottoman Turks, and the Hagia Sophia was converted into a mosque. Human images are not welcome in mosques, and many of the mosaics were covered with plaster. In 1934, Turkish President Kemal Atatürk turned the building into a museum. In recent years some restoration work has been done on the Hagia Sophia, and a few of the mosaics have been uncovered. Despite the ravages of time, the Hagia Sophia remains universally acknowledged as one of the most beautiful buildings in the world.\</item>
        <item>\The core of what is today the famed Hermitage in St. Petersburg encompasses the monumental Winter Palace, residence of the Tsars since 1764 AD when Catherine the Great completed the palace on a scale to reflect the might and power of Imperial Russia. Catherine declared it her “treasure,” and proceeded to fill it with treasures – Renaissance paintings, jeweled and gilded crafts (the likes of Fabergé eggs, for instance), the crown jewels, and other trinkets. After adding several extensions to the palace and some reorganizing, in 1852 Nicholas I opened it to the public. And the Tsars kept adding to the collection.\n\nWith the February Revolution of 1917, the building briefly housed the Provisional Government, until the Bolsheviks seized power in October and declared it a gift to the proletariat. Now spread across five buildings, the Hermitage is one of the largest museums in the world, with over three million art and historical items in its collection, including the largest gathering of paintings in the world.\</item>
        <item>\Serene, enduring, and somewhat mysterious, the Buddha statue known as the Daibutsu sits outside of Kamakura’s Kōtoku-in. Towering over the Buddhist temple’s visitors, the Daibutsu patiently greets both faithful and tourist alike. An unknown artist cast the Great Buddha of Kamakura out of bronze, which has since oxidized into a muted green color through natural weathering.\n\nHowever, the Kōtoku-in’s artist clearly built it to last. It survived an earthquake and two typhoons, one of which destroyed the building that used to surround it. The statue remains unfazed by nature’s attempts to unseat its 750-year meditation.\</item>
        <item>\The Louvre is a large and incredibly ornate palace in Paris, France. Originally constructed in the 15th century on the site of an even older castle, for the next two and a half centuries the Louvre served as the home to many of France\'s kings, most of whom added to the already-huge structure.\n\nDuring the 17th century Kings Louis XIII and Louis XIV and their advisors Cardinals Richelieu and Mazarin began acquiring an extensive art collection which was kept at the Louvre.\n\nIn 1682 the Royal court moved to Versailles, and in 1793 the Revolutionary government opened the palace to the public. It has remained a public museum ever since. Not surprisingly, it is considered to have the finest collection of pre-modern French paintings in the world.\</item>
        <item>\Clinging to a Peruvian mountaintop at an elevation of 2,350 m (7,700 feet), Machu Picchu was an extraordinary Incan city and a marvel of pre-Columbian architecture. Constructed in the mid-15th century, scholars believe that much of the city was a palace complex of the mighty Incan ruler Pachacuti Inca Yupanqui. Constructed almost entirely of white granite stone, the city was inexplicably deserted in the mid-16th century. The marauding Spanish Conquistadors did not discover the site during their conquest of the Incas, so it has remained relatively intact until today.\n\nArchaeologists have identified the aforementioned palace complex, as well as temples, residential areas, plazas and a cemetery, all carved from the living rock. The mountainous terrain surrounding the central structures has been carved into stepped agricultural terraces which were at one time watered by an extensive aqueduct system, in itself a remarkable feat in a mountainous locale.\n\nAlthough in ruins, Machu Picchu retains an extraordinary rugged beauty even today. It must have been an incredible city during the days when the mighty Incas called it home.\</item>
        <item>\The Mahabodhi Temple (or “Great Awakening” Temple) in Bodh Gaya is one of the four sacred sites of the Lord Buddha’s (Siddhartha Gautama) life, and the very spot where he attained Enlightenment. On the western side of the temple is the sacred Bodhi Tree, the very fig tree under which the Buddha was sitting when he did so. Be all that as it may, the first Mahabodhi Temple (there have been a couple) was built by the Emperor Asoka c. 250 BC.\n\nThe current temple complex – notably the great tower, one of the first brick structures in India – dates from the 5th and 6th centuries AD. A high wall around the temple grounds was added at a later, undocumented, date; the wall encompasses the Bodhi Tree and six other sacred site of Buddha’s very enlightenment, since he spent seven weeks in seven different spots meditating on his very own revelations, as well as numerous Votive stupas.\n\nIn the 1880s the British Raj undertook a restoration effort; in 1949 control of the very site passed to the state government of Bihar. Today, Buddhists from the world over make pilgrimage to Bodh Gaya as the holiest place of their very faith.\</item>
        <item>\The Meenakshi Amman Temple dates back to the first century and is one of the oldest temples in India, still receiving thousands of visitors daily. Devoted to the goddess Meenakshi, a representation of love and fertility, this colorful complex spans 14 acres and is composed of tall walls, various shrines, 14 Gopurams (ornate gatehouse towers), and several Manapams (pillared halls).\n\nBrightly painted ceilings and stone carvings can be throughout the complex, but it is perhaps the thousands of vibrant stone statues lining the towers that have become most iconic. These small sculptures depict moments from Hindu stories – gods, demons, heroes, and animals. Every twelve years, these works are repainted and repaired.\</item>
        <item>\Perched on a rocky islet between Normandy and Brittany in the midst of sandbanks washed over by ocean tides, Mont St. Michel is a Gothic-style Benedictine abbey dedicated to the archangel Micheal built between the 11th and 16th centuries. Besides St. Aubert\'s skull, the Mont also was repository for bits of St. Petroc and St. Olaf and other holy relics.\n\nThe place did have a practical purpose; its high walls, turrets and position made it of strategic worth … and many a French king stationed a small garrison (all that was needed) there. At low tide, it was readily accessible to pilgrims eager to give up a coin or two to be blessed; at high tide, the incoming sea would strand or drown any attacking force.\n\nThe Mont would remain unconquered throughout the Hundred Years\' War and beyond. Its position also made it ideal to incarcerate unrepentant traitors and other sinners; Louis XI turned the Mont into a prison, a role it served through the rest of the Ancien Régime.\n\nNow, it\'s still an abbey hosting a religious community, as well as a highly touristic visited place.\</item>
        <item>\Notre Dame is a mighty cathedral standing on the "Île de la Cité," an island in the Seine River in Paris, France. Built on the site of an older church, which was in turn built on the site of a Roman temple to Jupiter, Notre Dame is a magnificent example of gothic architecture and one of the greatest buildings standing. Construction of Notre Dame began in 1163 and took almost two centuries to complete.\n\nNotre Dame is a massive stone building of square towers, flying buttresses, and tall spires. The exterior is decorated with delicate ribbons of arches and statues of saints and kings. The roofline of the building is festooned with gargoyles. The interior of the cathedral is a long, narrow space with columns lining each side, supporting two beautiful raised galleries. Brilliant stained glass windows shine gently down on the main altar, which contains a beautiful statue of the Virgin Mary, the cathedral\'s patron, holding the body of Jesus.\n\nThe cathedral has suffered many periods of neglect over the years. During the French Revolution, many of Notre Dame\'s treasures were stolen and the building was used as a warehouse. In the early 1800s, the cathedral was in such a state of disrepair that the city planners contemplated tearing it down. In fact, Victor Hugo wrote "The Hunchback of Notre Dame" in part to raise awareness of the cathedral\'s plight. In 1871, during the short-lived Paris Commune, Notre Dame was almost set on fire. Fortunately the cathedral survived it all, and has now been largely restored to its original grandeur.\</item>
        <item>\Orszaghaz translates to “House of the Country” but is better known as the Hungarian Parliament Building. This important building houses the members of Parliament, Hungarian Holy Crown, and the offices of the Prime Minister and staff.\n\nBut aside from its significance to the government of Hungary, this building itself is an impressive display of Gothic Revival architecture. Overlooking the Danube River, the long wing spans 268 meters, and it is the tallest building in Budapest. Two identical halls for the Lower and Upper houses of Parliament stretch beyond a tall, central dome. Decorating the exterior façade are 90 stone sculptures that portray great moments of Hungarian history, as well as ornately carved stone.\n\nIf that wasn\'t enough to excite visitors to this grand building, the precious stones and 88 lbs of gold used for decoration should do the trick.\</item>
        <item>\Built upon the Acropolis, dedicated to the goddess Athena, the Parthenon is considered the culmination of Doric architecture. Construction of the temple began in 447 BC; the last decorations were put into place in 432 BC and are important surviving examples of classical sculpture. It housed the chryselephantine statute of Athena sculpted by Phidius, and the outer facade was ornamented with 92 metopes. Like most Greek temples, the Parthenon also served as treasury, both for Athens itself and for the Delian League.\n\nThrough the 1700s, European tourists and scholars enjoyed greater access to the picturesque ruins and its fame spread. When Greece regained its independence in 1832, the government took control of the site.\n\nUndertaking a restoration of the Acropolis in 1975, Greece has made the Parthenon an enduring symbol of ancient Greece, Athenian democratic ideals, Western civilization and one of the world\'s greatest cultural treasures.\</item>
        <item>\Situated between the Red Sea and the Dead Sea, Petra is a city cut from the red sandstone around Wadi Musa (now part of Jordan) by the Nabataeans – who obviously had a lot of free time – around 400 BC. Mentioned in Egyptian, Greek and Biblical sources, the city would develop into a major caravan center, a vital crossroads between Arabia, Egypt and Syria to the north. Surrounded by mountains riddled with gorges and canyon passages, it was defensible; but it was the ingenious and extensive system of cisterns and reservoirs in the middle of a desert that made it a trade center.\n\nAt its peak, Petra was home to perhaps 20 thousand inhabitants, and served as the capital of the Nabataean kingdom. That is, until the Romans arrived and annexed it in 106 AD. Struck by a series of earthquakes, as well as Roman taxes, it was essentially abandoned two hundred years after – not to be “discovered” until 1812 by the Swiss explorer Johann Burckhardt.\</item>
        <item>\Since there wasn’t much level ground in Tibet, with its base set on the southern slope of the Red Hill, the Potala Palace – home to the Dalai Lama (until the fourteenth one fled an uprising in 1959) – sort of grew along the hillside.\n\nThe palace is named after Mount Potalaka, abode of the eleven-headed bodhisattva Avalokiteśvara. Today, its crimson and white walls and golden roof “shine in glory” … for paying tourists. Lozang Gyatso, the fifth Dalai Lama, began construction of the “modern” palace above Lhasa c. 1645 AD, and moved in four years later.\n\nSince then more bits and pieces have been added to the sprawling edifice, notably the Potrang Marpo (“red palace”) and the holy stupa completed in 1694. However, it should be noted that the Potala Palace has only one bathroom, located on the right side of the White Palace Square … although it is said to be the most beautiful restroom on Earth, filled with sunlight and good thoughts.\</item>
        <item>\Though pyramids were built from the beginning of the Old Kingdom to the close of the Ptolemaic dynasty, the really big heaps of stone along the Nile were piled up commencing in the late third dynasty and continuing through the sixth (roughly 500 years). The Great Pyramid of Giza that is virtually synonymous with the “glory”  of ancient Egypt went up around 2560 BC to serve as the tomb of Pharaoh Khufu (who is unremarkable for anything else save the length of his reign).\n\nIt is considered one of the Seven Wonders of the Ancient World. Built by tens of thousands of workers, including skilled masons, and covered with “casing stones” (slabs of polished limestone), the Pyramids of Giza were a testament to Egypt’s power and the natives’ conviction of the afterlife – at least for the elite. To date, some 135 pyramids have been found in what was once the greatest empire in the world.\</item>
        <item>\The large, dramatically colored cathedral near Moscow’s Moskva River officially bore the name “Cathedral of the Intercession of the Virgin by the Moat,” but most people referred to it as “St. Basil’s.” Also, the shorter name fits better on maps. Ivan the Terrible commissioned its construction in 1555 to commemorate victories achieved during his reign.\n\nDespite Ivan’s namesake, the cathedral turned out to be anything but terrible. The cathedral is reminiscent of a Russian nesting doll, consisting of eight separate clustered churches rather than a single one. Though St. Basil’s was originally a drab white, it received a fresh coat of bold, patterned paint in 1860 that has defined it since.\</item>
        <item>\The Statue of Liberty is one of the largest statues in the world. Measuring over 90 meters (300 feet) tall from the base of its pedestal, the statue is constructed of copper plating over an iron framework and weighs over 250 metric tons. Designed by French sculptor Frederic Bartholdi, the statue, with upraised torch and the broken chains of tyranny at her feet, was presented to the United States by the French government in 1886 to commemorate 100 years of American independence. The statue itself, Liberty Island, and nearby Ellis Island became a national monument in 1924. During WWI the statue was damaged when German spies blew up a nearby ammo dump. The torch has been closed for visiting by the public since.\n\nFor more than a century, the Statue of Liberty has stood at the mouth of the New York harbor. Often the first sight seen by immigrants arriving in America, Lady Liberty symbolizes the ideals of freedom upon which the United States was founded.\</item>
        <item>\A circle of fifty-ton slabs of rock, arranged in orientation to the stars and sun, Stonehenge is an observatory and temple in one. Begun in Southern England some 5000 years ago, Stonehenge was concentric circles of stones surrounded by a moat (or “henge”). After the henge was in place, about a thousand years later an inner ring of “bluestones” were set in place, followed by an outer ring of larger, upright “sarsen” stones some 500 years after that. The 80 bluestones, coming in at about four tons each, were transported from a quarry over 240 miles away; the sarsen stones were cut and transported about 20 miles to the site. However done, for whatever purpose, Stonehenge remains a “wondrous” achievement even after a few millennia.\</item>
        <item>\The construction of an enormous arts center for Sydney on Bennelong Point had been debated since the 1940s; in 1956 AD the government of New South Wales announced an open-ended competition for the design of something grand to show the world that the city really did have some taste. \n\nA Danish architect, Jørn Utzon won with his unique expressionist design, a series of precast concrete “shells,” covered with over a million white- or cream-colored tiles with interior glass curtain walls. So unique was the problematic design (Utzon had paid no heed to structural engineering) that it took sixteen years to build at a cost ten times more than estimated. But, once completed and officially dedicated by Queen Elizabeth II in October 1973, it has since become the iconic symbol of the one-time penal colony.\n\nFrom its 2,679-seat grand Concert Hall to the intimate 210-seat Utzon Room, the Opera House brings performances of all sorts down under.\</item>
        <item>\The Taj Mahal stands in Agra, India. It was built in the mid-16th century at the orders of the Mughal Emperor Shah Jahan, as a mausoleum for his wife. Acknowledged as one of the most beautiful structures in the world, the Taj Mahal is composed of rare and brilliant materials imported from across India and Asia - it is said that over 1000 elephants were employed to carry the sandstone, marble, jade, turquoise, sapphires, and other materials used in its construction.\n\nThe Taj Mahal complex covers an area of approximately 300 meters by 580 meters (1000 feet by 1900 feet) and consists of a gateway, garden, mausoleum, mosque, and guest house. The first three buildings are clad in white marble and covered with geometric patterns, while the mosque and guesthouse are built of brilliant red sandstone. The buildings are topped with magnificent onion-shaped domes and minarets.\n\nExperts have debated about what makes the Taj Mahal unique and beautiful. Some suggest that it lies in the structures\' marvelous proportions and symmetry, while others argue in favor of the way that the marble buildings interact with the light, giving the Taj Mahal ever-changing character as the sun rises and sets. Still others believe that its inherent beauty lies in its purpose - a man seeking to cast in stone his love for his departed wife.\</item>
    </string-array>

    //People

    <string-array name="people_name">
        <item>ALEXANDER III</item>
        <item>AUGUSTUS CAESAR</item>
        <item>BELISARIUS</item>
        <item>CATHERINE III</item>
        <item>CHARLEMAGNE</item>
        <item>CYRUS II</item>
        <item>DARIUS I</item>
        <item>EDWARD III</item>
        <item>ELEANOR OF AQUITAINE</item>
        <item>ELIZABETH I</item>

        <item>FERDINAND MAGELLAN</item>
        <item>FREDERICK I BARBAROSSA</item>
        <item>FREDERICK II</item>
        <item>GALILEO GALILEI</item>
        <item>GUSTAVUS ADOLPHUS</item>
        <item>HORATIO NELSON</item>
        <item>Ivan IV Vasilyevich</item>
        <item>Joan of Arc</item>
        <item>Justinian I</item>
        <item>Pope Leo I</item>

        <item>Leonardo Da Vinci</item>
        <item>Leonidas</item>
        <item>Marco Polo</item>
        <item>Marcus Aurelius</item>
        <item>Mehmed II </item>
        <item>Napoleon Bonaparte</item>
        <item>Oliver Cromwell</item>
        <item>Otto von Bismarck </item>
        <item>Peter Romanov</item>
        <item>Richard I</item>

        <item>Robert I</item>
        <item>Saladin </item>
        <item>Suleiman I</item>
        <item>Tancred of Hauteville</item>
        <item>Theodora</item>
        <item>Trajan </item>
        <item>Vlad Dracula</item>
        <item>William Wallace</item>
        <item>Zenobia</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="people_title">
        <item>THE GREAT</item>
        <item>The First Citizen</item>
        <item>The Emperor\'s Sword</item>
        <item>Empress of All the Russians</item>
        <item>Carolus Magnus</item>
        <item>The First Persian Emperor</item>
        <item>King of Kings</item>
        <item>The Black Prince</item>
        <item>Queen Mother</item>
        <item>Good Queen Bess</item>

        <item>The First around the World</item>
        <item>Red Beard</item>
        <item>Old Fritz</item>
        <item>The Father of Astronomy</item>
        <item>The Lion from the North</item>
        <item>Britain\'s Most Beloved Sailor</item>
        <item>The First Tsar of Russia</item>
        <item>The Maid of Orléans</item>
        <item>The Impossible Burden of Fate</item>
        <item>The Lion and Steed</item>

        <item>The Rennaissance Man</item>
        <item>The King of Sparta</item>
        <item>The Traveler</item>
        <item>The Philosopher Emperor</item>
        <item>The Conqueror</item>
        <item>Emperor of France</item>
        <item>The Lord Protector</item>
        <item>The Iron Chancellor</item>
        <item>The Westernizer</item>
        <item>The Lionheart</item>

        <item>The Bruce</item>
        <item>The Righteous of the Faith</item>
        <item>The Lawgiver</item>
        <item>Regent of Antioch</item>
        <item>Purple is the Noblest Shroud</item>
        <item>Optimus Princeps</item>
        <item>The Impaler</item>
        <item>Braveheart</item>
        <item>Queen of Palmyra</item>
    </string-array>

    <string-array name="people_details">
        <item>\Alexander III of Macedon, better known as Alexander the Great, single-handedly changed the nature of the ancient world in little more than a decade.\n\Alexander was born in Pella, the ancient capital of Macedonia in July 356 BC. His parents were Philip II of Macedon and his wife Olympias. Alexander was educated by the philosopher Aristotle. Philip was assassinated in 336 BC and Alexander inherited a powerful yet volatile kingdom. He quickly dealt with his enemies at home and reasserted Macedonian power within Greece. He then set out to conquer the massive Persian Empire.\n\nAgainst overwhelming odds, he led his army to victories across the Persian territories of Asia Minor, Syria and Egypt without suffering a single defeat. His greatest victory was at the Battle of Gaugamela, in what is now northern Iraq, in 331 BC. The young king of Macedonia, leader of the Greeks, overlord of Asia Minor and pharaoh of Egypt became \'great king\' of Persia at the age of 25.\n\nOver the next eight years, in his capacity as king, commander, politician, scholar and explorer, Alexander led his army a further 11,000 miles, founding over 70 cities and creating an empire that stretched across three continents and covered around two million square miles. The entire area from Greece in the west, north to the Danube, south into Egypt and as far to the east as the Indian Punjab, was linked together in a vast international network of trade and commerce. This was united by a common Greek language and culture, while the king himself adopted foreign customs in order to rule his millions of ethnically diverse subjects.\n\nAlexander was acknowledged as a military genius who always led by example, although his belief in his own indestructibility meant he was often reckless with his own life and those of his soldiers. The fact that his army only refused to follow him once in 13 years of a reign during which there was constant fighting, indicates the loyalty he inspired.\n\nHe died of a fever in Babylon in June 323 BC.\</item>
        <item>\Augustus was born Gaius Octavius on 23 September 63 BC in Rome. In 43 BC his great-uncle, Julius Caesar, was assassinated and in his will, Octavius, known as Octavian, was named as his heir. He fought to avenge Caesar and in 31 BC defeated Antony and Cleopatra at the Battle of Actium. He was now undisputed ruler of Rome.\n\nInstead of following Caesar\'s example and making himself dictator, Octavian in 27 BC founded the principate, a system of monarchy headed by an emperor holding power for life. His powers were hidden behind constitutional forms, and he took the name Augustus meaning \'lofty\' or \'serene\'. Nevertheless, he retained ultimate control of all aspects of the Roman state, with the army under his direct command.\n\nAt home, he embarked on a large programme of reconstruction and social reform. Rome was transformed with impressive new buildings and Augustus was a patron to Virgil, Horace and Propertius, the leading poets of the day. Augustus also ensured that his image was promoted throughout his empire by means of statues and coins.\n\nAbroad, he created a standing army for the first time, and embarked upon a vigorous campaign of expansion designed to make Rome safe from the \'barbarians\' beyond the frontiers, and to secure the Augustan peace. His stepsons Tiberius and Drusus undertook the task (Augustus had married their mother Livia in 38 BC). Between 16 BC and 6 AD the frontier was advanced from the Rhine to the Elbe in Germany, and up to the Danube along its entire length. But Drusus died in the process and in 9 AD the annihilation of three Roman legions in Germany (out of 28 overall), in the Varian disaster, led to the abandonment of Germany east of the Rhine.\n\nAugustus was determined to be succeeded by someone of his own blood, but he had no sons, only a daughter, Julia, the child of his first wife. His nephew Marcellus and his beloved grandsons Gaius and Lucius pre-deceased him, so he reluctantly made Tiberius his heir.\n\nMilitary disaster, the loss of his grandsons and a troubled economy clouded his last years. He became more dictatorial, exiling the poet Ovid (8 AD), who had mocked his moral reforms. He died on 19 August 14 AD.\</item>
        <item>\Flavius Belisarius (l. 505-565 CE) was born in Illyria (the western part of the Balkan Peninsula) to poor parents and rose to become one of the greatest generals, if not the greatest, of the Byzantine Empire. Belisarius is listed among the notable candidates for the title of \'Last of the Romans\' by which is meant the last individual who most perfectly embodies the values of the Roman Empire at its best. He served as commander of the military under the Byzantine Emperor Justinian I (r. 527-565 CE) with whom he had a notoriously difficult relationship.\n\nHe first enlisted in the army under the Byzantine emperor Justin I (r. 518-527 CE) and, upon Justin\'s death, his successor, Justinian I, awarded Belisarius full command of the army. He put down the Nika uprising in Constantinople in 532 CE, the result of resentment against Justinian I, slaughtering between 20-30,000 people. He then commanded Byzantine forces against the Persians, Vandals, Goths, and Bulgars, serving the empire nobly and faithfully until his death.\</item>
        <item>\Sophie Friederike Auguste von Anhalt-Zerbst was born on 2 May 1729 in Stettin, then part of Prussia (now Szczecin in Poland), the daughter of a minor German prince. In 1745, after being received into the Russian Orthodox Church, and changing her name to Catherine, she married Grand Duke Peter, grandson of Peter the Great and heir to the Russian throne.\n\nThe marriage was unhappy, but the couple did produce one son, Paul. In 1762 Catherine\'s husband became Tsar Peter III but he was soon overthrown with Catherine being declared empress. Peter was then killed shortly afterwards and it is not known whether Catherine had a part in his death. She subsequently had a series of lovers whom she promoted to high office, the most famous and successful of whom was Grigori Potemkin.\n\nCatherine\'s major influences on her adopted country were in expanding Russia\'s borders and continuing the process of Westernisation begun by Peter the Great. During her reign she extended the Russian empire southwards and westwards, adding territories which included the Crimea, Belarus and Lithuania. Agreements with Prussia and Austria led to three partitions of Poland, in 1772, 1793, and 1795, extending Russia\'s borders well into central Europe.\n\nCatherine began as a political and social reformer but gradually grew more conservative as she got older. In 1767 she convened the Legislative Commission to codify Russia\'s laws and in the process modernised Russian life. She presented the commission with her Nakaz, (or \'Instruction\'), a strikingly liberal document that presented the empress’s vision of the ideal government. The commission produced no desired results and the outbreak of war against the Ottoman Empire in 1768 provided a good opportunity to disband it.\n\nThe Pugachev Rebellion of 1774-1775 gained huge support in Russia\'s western territories until it was extinguished by the Russian army. Catherine realised her heavy reliance on the nobility to control the country and instigated a series of reforms giving them greater control over their land and serfs. The 1785 ‘Charter to the Nobility’ established them as a separate estate in Russian society and assured their privileges. Catherine therefore ignored any concern she may previously have had for the plight of the serfs, whose status and rights declined further.\n\nCatherine\'s main interests were in education and culture. She read widely and corresponded with many of the prominent thinkers of the era, including Voltaire and Diderot. She was a patron of the arts, literature and education and acquired an art collection which now forms the basis of the Hermitage Museum.\n\nCatherine died in St Petersburg on 17 November 1796 and was succeeded by her son Paul.\</item>
        <item>\Charlemagne was born in the late 740s near Liège in modern day Belgium, the son of the Frankish king Pepin the Short. When Pepin died in 768, his kingdom was divided between his two sons and for three years Charlemagne ruled with his younger brother Carloman. When Carloman died suddenly in 771, Charlemagne became sole ruler.\n\nCharlemagne spent the early part of his reign on several military campaigns to expand his kingdom. He invaded Saxony in 772 and eventually achieved its total conquest and conversion to Christianity. He also extended his dominance to the south, conquering the kingdom of the Lombards in northern Italy. In 778, he invaded northern Spain, then controlled by the Moors. Between 780 and 800, Charlemagne added Bohemia to his empire and subdued the Avars in the middle Danube basin to form a buffer state for the eastern border of his empire.\n\nIn 800 a rebellion against Pope Leo III began. Charlemagne went to his aid in Rome and defeated the rebellion. As a token of thanks, Leo crowned Charlemagne on Christmas Day that year, declaring him emperor of the Romans. Although this did not give Charlemagne any new powers, it legitimised his rule over his Italian territories and attempted to revive the imperial tradition of the western Roman emperor.\n\nThe immense territories which Charlemagne controlled became known as the Carolingian empire. Charlemagne introduced administrative reforms throughout the lands he controlled, establishing key representatives in each region and holding a general assembly each year at his court at Aachen. He standardised weights, measures and customs dues, which helped improve commerce and initiated important legal reforms. He also attempted to consolidate Christianity throughout his vast empire. He persuaded many eminent scholars to come to his court and established a new library of Christian and classical works.\n\nCharlemagne died in 814. His successors lacked his vision and authority, and his empire did not long outlive him.\</item>
        <item>\Cyrus (580-529 BC) was the first Achaemenid Emperor. He founded Persia by uniting the two original Iranian Tribes- the Medes and the Persians. Although he was known to be a great conqueror, who at one point controlled one of the greatest Empires ever seen, he is best remembered for his unprecedented tolerance and magnanimous attitude towards those he defeated.\n\nUpon his victory over the Medes, he founded a government for his new kingdom, incorporating both Median and Persian nobles as civilian officials. The conquest of Asia Minor completed, he led his armies to the eastern frontiers. Hyrcania and Parthia were already part of the Median Kingdom. Further east, he conquered Drangiana, Arachosia, Margiana and Bactria. After crossing the Oxus, he reached the Jaxartes, where he built fortified towns with the object of defending the farthest frontier of his kingdom against nomadic tribes of Central Asia.\n\nThe victories to the east led him again to the west and sounded the hour for attack on Babylon and Egypt. When he conquered Babylon, he did so to cheers from the Jewish Community, who welcomed him as a liberator- he allowed the Jews to return to the promised Land. He showed great forbearance and respect towards the religious beliefs and cultural traditions of other races. These qualities earned him the respect and homage of all the people over whom he ruled.\n\nBas-Relief of Cyrus the Great, in Pasargad, IranThe victory over Babylonia expressed all the facets of the policy of conciliation which Cyrus had followed until then. He presented himself not as a conqueror, but a liberator and the legitimate successor to the crown. He also declared the first Charter of Human Rights known to mankind. He took the title of "King of Babylon and King of the Land". Cyrus had no thought of forcing conquered people into a single mould, and had the wisdom to leave unchanged the institution of each kingdom he attached to the Persian Crown. In 539 BCE he allowed more than 40,000 Jews to leave Babylon and return to Palestine. This step was in line with his policy to bring peace to Mankind. A new wind was blowing from the east, carrying away the cries and humility of defeated and murdered victims, extinguishing the fires of sacked cities, and liberating nations from slavery.\n\nCyrus was upright, a great leader of men, generous and benelovent. The Hellenes, whom he conquered regarded him as \'Law-giver\' and the Jews as \'the annointed of the Lord\'.\n\nPrior to his death, he founded a new capital city at Pasargade in Fars. and had established a government for his Empire. He appointed a governor (satrap) to represent him in each province, however the administration, legistlation, and cultural activities of each province was the responsibility of the Satraps. Accoding to Xenophon Cyrus is also reputed to have devised the first postal system, (Achaemenide achievements). His doctrines were adopted by the future emperors of the Achaemenian dynasty.\</item>
        <item>\Darius I Hystaspes, or Darius the Great, king of Persia [522-486 BCE]. Through his father Hystaspes, Darius belonged to the Achaemenid family, as did Cyrus The Great and his son Cambyses II, but to a different branch of this family. When Cambyses was in Egypt, during the last year of his reign, a certain Gaumata usurped the throne by pretending to be Bardiya, Cambyses\' brother, who had been assassinated secretly before Cambyses started out for his Egyptian campaign in 525 BCE. When Cambyses learned of this usurpation he immediately set out for Persia, but on the way, while in Syria, he died in July, 522 BCE, as the result of either an accident or suicide, leaving no heir. Darius, a distant cousin of Cambyses, at once set out to gain the throne for himself. With some helpers he slew the Smerdis/Gaumâta or false Bardiya in September, 522 BCE, and assumed the kingship. However, he had to fight against a number of other pretenders and rebels. It took more than a year (522-521 BCE) of hard fighting to put down revolts associated with Bardiya\'s claim to the throne. Almost every province of the empire was involved in the conflict, including Persia and, most particularly, Media. He finally emerged from the struggle the undisputed ruler of the Persian Empire. The story of his successes was engraved in three scripts and languages (Persian, Babylonian, and Elamite), accompanied by a sculptured relief, into a high rock wall of the Bisitun Mountain, a few miles east of modern Kermanshah.\n\nDarius proved to be a strong and wise ruler. He was tolerant toward other religions and cultures, promoted learning, agriculture, forestation, and the construction of highways. He also built the great palace cities of Susa and Persepolis.\n\nSuch activities, however, did not prevent Darius from following an active expansionist policy. Campaigns to the east confirmed gains probably made by Cyrus the Great and added large sections of the northern Indian subcontinent to the list of Persian-controlled provinces. Expansion in the west began about 516 BC when Darius moved against the Hellespont as a first step toward an attack on the Scythians along the western and northern shores of the Black Sea. The real strategic purpose behind this move probably was to disrupt and if possible to interrupt Greek trade with the Black Sea area, which supplied much grain to Greece. Crossing into Europe for the first time, Darius campaigned with comparatively little success to the north of the Danube. He retreated in good order, however, with only limited losses, and a bridgehead across the Hellespont was established.\n\nBy 492 BCE Darius made his son-in-law (Mardonius) special commissioner to Ionia. Mardonius had recovered Persian Thrace and Macedonia, first gained in the campaign against the Scythians and lost during the Ionian Revolt. There followed the Persian invasion of Greece that led to Darius\' defeat at the Battle of Marathon late in the summer of 490 BCE. The "Great King" was forced to retreat and to face the fact that the Greek problem, which had probably seemed to the Persians a minor issue on the western extremity of the empire, would require a more concerted and massive effort. Thus began preparations for an invasion of Greece on a grand, coordinated scale. These plans were interrupted in 486 BCE by two events: a serious revolt in Egypt, and the death of Darius.\</item>
        <item>\Edward was born on 15 June 1330 at Woodstock in Oxfordshire, the eldest son of Edward III. He was created prince of Wales in 1343. He showed military brilliance at an early age, playing a key role in the defeat of the French army at the Battle of Crecy when he was only 16. In 1355, he was appointed his father\'s lieutenant in Gascony and the following year led another significant victory against the French at Poitiers, taking the French king prisoner.\n\nIn 1362, Edward married Joan of Kent and was created prince of Aquitaine and Gascony by his father. Edward and his wife went to live in his new French domains. In 1367, Edward led an expedition to Spain, to restore the deposed King Pedro of Castile, and proved himself again with victory at the Battle of Najera in northern Castile. Edward returned to Aquitaine, where he made himself unpopular with the nobility by levying taxes to pay for his Spanish expedition. They rose in revolt against him and in 1370 Edward besieged the city of Limoges. When it fell, 3,000 of its inhabitants were massacred. A year later, Edward returned to England.\n\nEdward died aged 45 on 8 June 1376, probably from an illness contracted in Spain, and was buried in great splendour in Canterbury Cathedral. His young son, Richard, succeeded Edward III a year later.\n\nDuring his lifetime he was known as Edward of Woodstock. The title of Black Prince developed after his death and may refer to black armour that he wore.\</item>
        <item>\Eleanor was the elder daughter of William, tenth Duke of Aquitaine. The exact date of her birth is unknown, but she was raised in one of Europe\'s most cultured courts and given an excellent education. She later became an important patron of poets and writers.\n\nThe death of Eleanor\'s only brother, and of her father in 1137, left her with a vast inheritance. At just 15-years-old, she had suddenly become the most eligible heiress in Europe. That same year she married Louis, heir to Louis VI of France, who shortly afterwards became king as Louis VII. The couple had two daughters.\n\nIn 1147, Eleanor accompanied her husband on the Second Crusade, travelling to Constantinople and Jerusalem. The Crusade was a failure and relations between Eleanor and her husband, already poor, deteriorated even further. Eleanor\'s failure to produce a son contributed considerably to this tension, and in 1152 they were divorced.\n\nTwo months later Eleanor married Henry of Anjou, who in 1154 became king of England. The couple had five sons and three daughters. For nearly two decades, Eleanor played an active part in the running of Henry\'s empire, travelling backwards and forwards between their territories in England and France.\n\nIn 1173 two of Eleanor\'s sons involved her in a plot against their father, and as a result Henry imprisoned her. After Henry\'s death in 1189, his eldest son, Richard I, ordered his mother\'s release. Despite her age (now in her mid-sixties, which was considered elderly in the 12th century) Eleanor became very closely involved in government. In 1190, she acted as regent in England when Richard went to join the Third Crusade. She even played her part in negotiations for his release after he was taken prisoner in Germany on his way home.\n\nIn 1199, Richard died and was succeeded by Eleanor and Henry\'s youngest son, John. Eleanor\'s role in English affairs now ceased, although she continued to be closely involved in those of Aquitaine, where she spent her final years. She died on 31 March 1204 and was buried in the abbey church at Fontevrault next to Henry II.\</item>
        <item>\Her early life was full of uncertainties, and her chances of succeeding to the throne seemed very slight once her half-brother Edward was born in 1537. She was then third in line behind her Roman Catholic half-sister, Princess Mary. Roman Catholics, indeed, always considered her illegitimate and she only narrowly escaped execution in the wake of a failed rebellion against Queen Mary in 1554.\n\nElizabeth succeeded to the throne on her half-sister\'s death in November 1558. She was very well-educated (fluent in five languages), and had inherited intelligence, determination and shrewdness from both parents.\n\nHer 45-year reign is generally considered one of the most glorious in English history. During it a secure Church of England was established. Its doctrines were laid down in the 39 Articles of 1563, a compromise between Roman Catholicism and Protestantism.\n\nElizabeth herself refused to \'make windows into men\'s souls ... there is only one Jesus Christ and all the rest is a dispute over trifles\'; she asked for outward uniformity.\n\nMost of her subjects accepted the compromise as the basis of their faith, and her church settlement probably saved England from religious wars like those which France suffered in the second half of the 16th century.\n\nAlthough autocratic and capricious, Elizabeth had astute political judgement and chose her ministers well; these included William Cecil, later Lord Burghley (Secretary of State), Sir Christopher Hatton (Lord Chancellor) and Sir Francis Walsingham (in charge of intelligence and also a Secretary of State).\n\nOverall, Elizabeth\'s administration consisted of some 600 officials administering the great offices of state, and a similar number dealing with the Crown lands (which funded the administrative costs). Social and economic regulation and law and order remained in the hands of the sheriffs at local level, supported by unpaid justices of the peace.\n\nElizabeth\'s reign also saw many brave voyages of discovery, including those of Francis Drake, Walter Raleigh and Humphrey Gilbert, particularly to the Americas. These expeditions prepared England for an age of colonisation and trade expansion, which Elizabeth herself recognised by establishing the East India Company in at the very end of 1599.\n\nThe arts flourished during Elizabeth\'s reign. Country houses such as Longleat and Hardwick Hall were built, miniature painting reached its high point, theatres thrived - the Queen attended the first performance of Shakespeare\'s \'A Midsummer Night\'s Dream\'. Composers such as William Byrd and Thomas Tallis worked in Elizabeth\'s court and at the Chapel Royal, St. James\'s Palace.\n\nThe image of Elizabeth\'s reign is one of triumph and success. The Queen herself was often called \'Gloriana\', \'Good Queen Bess\' and \'The Virgin Queen\'.\n\nInvesting in expensive clothes and jewellery (to look the part, like all contemporary sovereigns), she cultivated this image by touring the country in regional visits known as \'progresses\', often riding on horseback rather than by carriage. Elizabeth made at least 25 progresses during her reign.\n\nHowever, Elizabeth\'s reign was one of considerable danger and difficulty for many, with threats of invasion from Spain through Ireland, and from France through Scotland. Much of northern England was in rebellion in 1569-70. A papal bull of 1570 specifically released Elizabeth\'s subjects from their allegiance, and she passed harsh laws against Roman Catholics after plots against her life were discovered.\n\nOne such plot involved Mary, Queen of Scots, who had fled to England in 1568 after her second husband, Henry, Lord Darnley\'s, murder and her subsequent marriage to a man believed to have been involved in his murder, James, Earl of Bothwell.\n\nAs a likely successor to Elizabeth, Mary spent 19 years as Elizabeth\'s prisoner because Mary was the focus for rebellion and possible assassination plots, such as the Babington Plot of 1586.\n\nMary was also a temptation for potential invaders such as Philip II. In a letter of 1586 to Mary, Elizabeth wrote, \'You have planned ... to take my life and ruin my kingdom ... I never proceeded so harshly against you.\' Despite Elizabeth\'s reluctance to take drastic action, on the insistence of Parliament and her advisers, Mary was tried, found guilty and executed in 1587.\n\nIn 1588, aided by bad weather, the English navy scored a great victory over the Spanish invasion fleet of around 130 ships - the \'Armada\'. The Spanish Armada was intended to overthrow the Queen and re-establish Roman Catholicism by conquest, as Philip II believed he had a claim to the English throne through his marriage to Mary.\n\nDuring Elizabeth\'s long reign, the nation also suffered from high prices and severe economic depression, especially in the countryside, during the 1590s. The war against Spain was not very successful after the Armada had been beaten and, together with other campaigns, it was very costly.\n\nThough she kept a tight rein on government expenditure, Elizabeth left large debts to her successor. Wars during Elizabeth\'s reign are estimated to have cost over £5 million (at the prices of the time) which Crown revenues could not match - in 1588, for example, Elizabeth\'s total annual revenue amounted to some £392,000.\n\nDespite the combination of financial strains and prolonged war after 1588, Parliament was not summoned more often. There were only 16 sittings of the Commons during Elizabeth\'s reign, five of which were in the period 1588-1601. Although Elizabeth freely used her power to veto legislation, she avoided confrontation and did not attempt to define Parliament\'s constitutional position and rights.\n\nElizabeth chose never to marry. If she had chosen a foreign prince, he would have drawn England into foreign policies for his own advantages (as in her sister Mary\'s marriage to Philip of Spain); marrying a fellow countryman could have drawn the Queen into factional infighting. Elizabeth used her marriage prospects as a political tool in foreign and domestic policies.\n\nHowever, the \'Virgin Queen\' was presented as a selfless woman who sacrificed personal happiness for the good of the nation, to which she was, in essence, \'married\'.\n\nLate in her reign, she addressed Parliament in the so-called \'Golden Speech\' of 1601 when she told MPs: \'There is no jewel, be it of never so high a price, which I set before this jewel; I mean your love.\' She seems to have been very popular with the vast majority of her subjects.\n\nOverall, Elizabeth\'s always shrewd and, when necessary, decisive leadership brought successes during a period of great danger both at home and abroad. She died at Richmond Palace on 24 March 1603, having become a legend in her lifetime. The date of her accession was a national holiday for two hundred years. James VI of Scotland was Elizabeth\'s successor and became James I of England.\</item>

        <item>\Ferdinand Magellan was born in 1480 into a noble Portuguese family. His parents died when he was still a boy and he became a court page in Lisbon. In 1505, he enlisted in the fleet of the Portuguese viceroy to the Indies, and spent the following years involved in a series of Portuguese expeditions in India and Africa. In 1511, he was with the fleet that conquered Malacca (on the Malay Peninsula), thus gaining control of the most important trade routes in the region. He also explored the islands of present-day Indonesia as far east as the Moluccas (also known as the Spice Islands).\n\nIn 1512, Magellan returned to Lisbon, and the following year, he was wounded during an expedition to Morocco, which left him with a permanent limp. After a disagreement with the Portuguese king, in 1517 Magellan went to Spain to try and enlist the Spanish king\'s support for an expedition to reach the Moluccas by sailing westwards. The Spanish wanted a share in the valuable spice trade from the Moluccas, but the Portuguese controlled the eastwards route round southern Africa. Magellan was successful and in September 1519 set out with a fleet of five vessels. In spite of a mutinous crew, rough weather, scurvy, a desperate lack of provisions and unknown waters, Magellan managed to cross the Atlantic and navigate through the straits at the southern point of South America which were later named after him.\n\nNow with only three ships, Magellan sailed on into the Pacific with rapidly diminishing supplies, which led to many of the crew dying of starvation and scurvy. After around 14 weeks they reached an island, probably Guam, in the western Pacific. They then sailed on to the Philippines. On 27 April 1521, Magellan was killed there after becoming involved in a battle between two rival local chieftains.\n\nOne ship from the fleet eventually reached Spain in September 1522, having completed the first ever circumnavigation of the globe.\</item>
        <item>\Frederick Barbarossa (1122 – 10 June 1190), also known as Frederick I, was the Holy Roman Emperor from 1155 until his death 35 years later. He was elected King of Germany at Frankfurt on 4 March 1152 and crowned in Aachen on 9 March 1152. He was crowned King of Italy on 24 April 1155 in Pavia and emperor by Pope Adrian IV on 18 June 1155 in Rome. Two years later, the term sacrum ("holy") first appeared in a document in connection with his empire. He was later formally crowned King of Burgundy, at Arles on 30 June 1178. He was named Barbarossa by the northern Italian cities which he attempted to rule: Barbarossa means "red beard" in Italian; in German, he was known as Kaiser Rotbart, which means "Emperor Redbeard" in English. The prevalence of the Italian nickname, even in later German usage, reflects the centrality of the Italian campaigns to his career.\n\nBefore his imperial election, Frederick was by inheritance Duke of Swabia. He was the son of Duke Frederick II of the Hohenstaufen dynasty and Judith, daughter of Henry IX, Duke of Bavaria, from the rival House of Welf. Frederick, therefore, descended from the two leading families in Germany, making him an acceptable choice for the Empire\'s prince-electors.\n\nHistorians consider him among the Holy Roman Empire\'s greatest medieval emperors. He combined qualities that made him appear almost superhuman to his contemporaries: his longevity, his ambition, his extraordinary skills at organization, his battlefield acumen and his political perspicacity. His contributions to Central European society and culture include the reestablishment of the Corpus Juris Civilis, or the Roman rule of law, which counterbalanced the papal power that dominated the German states since the conclusion of the Investiture Controversy.\n\nDue to his popularity and notoriety, in the nineteenth and early twentieth centuries, he was instrumentalized as a political symbol by many movements and regimes: the Risorgimento, the Wilhelmine government in Germany and the National Socialist movement, resulting in both golden and dark legends.Modern researchers, while exploring the legacy of Frederick, attempt to uncover the legends and reconstruct the true historical figure—these efforts result in new perspectives on both the emperor as a person and social developments associated with him.\n\nFrederick died in 1190 in Asia Minor while leading an army in the Third Crusade.\</item>
        <item>\Frederick II was King in Prussia from 1740 until 1772, and King of Prussia from 1772 until his death. His most significant accomplishments include his military successes in the Silesian wars, his re-organisation of the Prussian Army, the First Partition of Poland, and his patronage of the arts and the Enlightenment. Frederick was the last Hohenzollern monarch titled King in Prussia and declared himself King of Prussia after annexing Polish Prussia from the Polish–Lithuanian Commonwealth in 1772. Prussia greatly increased its territories and became a major military power in Europe under his rule. \n\nIn his youth, Frederick was more interested in music and philosophy than the art of war, which led to clashes with his authoritarian father, Frederick William I of Prussia. However, upon ascending to the Prussian throne, he attacked and annexed the rich Austrian province of Silesia in 1742, winning military acclaim for himself and Prussia. He then became an influential military theorist whose analysis emerged from his extensive personal battlefield experience and covered issues of strategy, tactics, mobility and logistics.\n\nFrederick was a supporter of enlightened absolutism, stating that the ruler should be the first servant of the state. He modernised the Prussian bureaucracy and civil service, and pursued religious policies throughout his realm that ranged from tolerance to segregation. He reformed the judicial system and made it possible for men of lower status to become judges and senior bureaucrats. Frederick also encouraged immigrants of various nationalities and faiths to come to Prussia, although he enacted oppressive measures against Catholics in Silesia and Polish Prussia. He supported the arts and philosophers he favoured, and allowed freedom of the press and literature. Frederick was almost certainly homosexual, and his sexuality has been the subject of much study. He is buried at his favourite residence, Sanssouci in Potsdam. Because he died childless, he was succeeded by his nephew, Frederick William II.\</item>
        <item>\Galileo Galilei was born on 15 February 1564 near Pisa, the son of a musician. He began to study medicine at the University of Pisa but changed to philosophy and mathematics. In 1589, he became professor of mathematics at Pisa. In 1592, he moved to become mathematics professor at the University of Padua, a position he held until 1610. During this time he worked on a variety of experiments, including the speed at which different objects fall, mechanics and pendulums.\n\nIn 1609, Galileo heard about the invention of the telescope in Holland. Without having seen an example, he constructed a superior version and made many astronomical discoveries. These included mountains and valleys on the surface of the moon, sunspots, the four largest moons of the planet Jupiter and the phases of the planet Venus. His work on astronomy made him famous and he was appointed court mathematician in Florence.\n\nIn 1614, Galileo was accused of heresy for his support of the Copernican theory that the sun was at the centre of the solar system. This was revolutionary at a time when most people believed the Earth was in this central position. In 1616, he was forbidden by the church from teaching or advocating these theories.\n\nIn 1632, he was again condemned for heresy after his book \'Dialogue Concerning the Two Chief World Systems\' was published. This set out the arguments for and against the Copernican theory in the form of a discussion between two men. Galileo was summoned to appear before the Inquisition in Rome. He was convicted and sentenced to life imprisonment, later reduced to permanent house arrest at his villa in Arcetri, south of Florence. He was also forced to publicly withdraw his support for Copernican theory.\n\nAlthough he was now going blind he continued to write. In 1638, his \'Discourses Concerning Two New Sciences\' was published with Galileo\'s ideas on the laws of motion and the principles of mechanics. Galileo died in Arcetri on 8 January 1642.\</item>
        <item>\Gustavus Adolphus was born in Stockholm as the oldest son of King Charles IX of Sweden of the Vasa dynasty and his second wife, Christina of Holstein-Gottorp. Upon his father\'s death in 1611, a seventeen year-old Gustav inherited the throne, as well as an ongoing succession of occasionally belligerent dynastic disputes with his Polish cousin, Sigismund III of Poland, who in the preliminary religious strife before the Thirty Years\' War, was forced to let go of the throne of Sweden to Gustav\'s father. Sigismund III wanted to regain the throne of Sweden and tried to force Gustav Adolph to renounce the title.\n\nIn a round of this dynastic dispute, he invaded Livonia when he was 31, beginning the Polish-Swedish War (1625–1629). He intervened on behalf of the Lutherans in Prussia, who opened the gates to their cities. His reign became famous from his actions a few years later when in June 1630, he landed in Germany, continuing Sweden\'s involvement in the ongoing Thirty Years\' War. Gustavus intervened on the anti-Imperial side, which at the time was losing to the Holy Roman Empire and its Catholic allies; the Swedish forces would quickly reverse that situation.\n\nHe was married to Maria Eleonora of Brandenburg, the daughter of John Sigismund, Elector of Brandenburg, and chose the Prussian city of Elbing as the base for his operations in Germany. He died in the Battle of Lützen in 1632. His early death was a great loss to the Lutheran side, it prolonged the war for many years. It resulted in large parts of Germany and other countries, who for a large part had become Lutheran in faith, to be forced into Catholicism (via Counter-Reformation). His involvement in the Thirty Years\' War gave rise to the old prophecy that he was the incarnation of "the Lion of the North," or as it is called in German "Der Löwe von Mitternacht" (Literally: "The Lion from Midnight").\</item>
        <item>\Born on 29 September 1758 in Burnham Thorpe, Norfolk, Horatio Nelson was the sixth of the 11 children of a clergyman. He joined the navy aged 12, on a ship commanded by a maternal uncle. He became a captain at 20, and saw service in the West Indies, Baltic and Canada. He married Frances Nisbet in 1787 in Nevis, and returned to England with his bride to spend the next five years on half-pay, frustrated at the lack of a command.\n\nWhen Britain entered the French Revolutionary Wars in 1793, Nelson was given command of the Agamemnon. He served in the Mediterranean, helped capture Corsica and saw battle at Calvi (where he lost the sight in his right eye). He would later lose his right arm at the Battle of Santa Cruz de Tenerife in 1797.\n\nAs a commander he was known for bold action, and the occasional disregard of orders from his seniors. This defiance brought him victories against the Spanish off Cape Vincent in 1797, and at the Battle of Copenhagen four years later, where he ignored orders to cease action by putting his telescope to his blind eye and claiming he couldn\'t seen the signal to withdraw.\n\nAt the Battle of the Nile in 1798, he successfully destroyed Napoleon\'s fleet and thus his bid for a direct trade route to India. Nelson\'s next posting took him to Naples, where he fell in love with Emma, Lady Hamilton. Although they remained in their respective marriages, Nelson and Emma Hamilton considered each other soul-mates and had a child together, Horatia, in 1801. Earlier that same year, Nelson was promoted to vice-admiral.\n\nOver the period 1794 to 1805, under Nelson\'s leadership, the Royal Navy proved its supremacy over the French. His most famous engagement, at Cape Trafalgar, saved Britain from threat of invasion by Napoleon, but it would be his last. Before the battle on 21 October 1805, Nelson sent out the famous signal to his fleet \'England expects that every man will do his duty\'. He was killed by a French sniper a few hours later while leading the attack on the combined French and Spanish fleet. His body was preserved in brandy and transported back to England where he was given a state funeral.\</item>
        <item>\Ivan the Terrible was the first tsar of all Russia. During his reign, he acquired vast amounts of land through ruthless means, creating a centrally controlled government.\n\nThe grandson of Ivan the Great, Ivan the Terrible, or Ivan IV, acquired vast amounts of land during his long reign, an era marked by the conquest of the khanates of Kazan, Astrakhan and Siberia. Ivan the Terrible created a centrally controlled Russian state, imposed by military dominance. Many believe him to have been mentally ill. One of his violent outbursts was perhaps the reason for his son\'s death.\n\nThe first tsar of all Russia, Ivan the Terrible, or Ivan IV, had a complex personality. Intelligent yet prone to outbreaks of uncontrollable rage, Ivan\'s tragic background contributed to his infamous behavior. Not a lot of detail is known about his early life, and historians debate his accomplishments as a leader. However, it is generally agreed that his reign established the current Russian territory and centralized government for centuries to come. \</item>
        <item>\Born in 1412 to Jacques and Isabelle d’Arc in domrémy, France. Her mother taught her domestic skills and religion, and she was known throughout the region for her kindness to others. During her childhood, France was fighting a war not only against the English but also against a French splinter group from Burgundy.\n\nWhen she was 13, Jeanne began hearing revelations from God through the voices of Saint Michael, Saint Catherine and Saint Margaret. Over the next five years, these voices instructed her to lead the siege at Orleans, and bring Charles to Reims for his crowning — and drive out the invading English troops.\n\nIn February of 1429, she traveled to Chinon where she met with the Dauphin Charles on March 9th. She received the Dauphin’s approval to win back the city of Orleans which she and her men took in just one week. In July of 1429, the Dauphin Charles was crowned King of France in the cathedral in Reims.\n\nAfter his crowning, the king soon lost interest in Jeanne’s advice. But she kept fighting on until she was captured in battle against the Burgundians. After a year she was handed over to the English by the Burgundians. The English condemned Jeanne as a witch and a heretic. She was finally burnt at the stake in market square in Rouen on May 30th, 1431.\n\nIn 1920, almost 500 years later, Pope Benedict XV read the bull of canonization declaring her a saint.\n\nThe details of the life of Jeanne d’Arc form a biography which is unique among the world’s biographies in one respect: It is the only story of a human life which comes to us under oath, the only one which comes to us from the witness-stand.\</item>
        <item>\Justinian I, also known as Justinian the Great, was the Byzantine emperor from 527 to 565.\n\nHis reign is marked by the ambitious but only partly realized renovatio imperii, or "restoration of the Empire". This ambition was expressed by the partial recovery of the territories of the defunct Western Roman Empire. His general, Belisarius, swiftly conquered the Vandal Kingdom in North Africa. Subsequently, Belisarius, Narses, and other generals conquered the Ostrogothic kingdom, restoring Dalmatia, Sicily, Italy, and Rome to the empire after more than half a century of rule by the Ostrogoths. The praetorian prefect Liberius reclaimed the south of the Iberian peninsula, establishing the province of Spania. These campaigns re-established Roman control over the western Mediterranean, increasing the Empire\'s annual revenue by over a million solidi. During his reign, Justinian also subdued the Tzani, a people on the east coast of the Black Sea that had never been under Roman rule before. He engaged the Sasanian Empire in the east during Kavad I\'s reign, and later again during Khosrow I\'s reign; this second conflict was partially initiated due to his ambitions in the west.\n\nA still more resonant aspect of his legacy was the uniform rewriting of Roman law, the Corpus Juris Civilis, which is still the basis of civil law in many modern states. His reign also marked a blossoming of Byzantine culture, and his building program yielded works such as the Hagia Sophia. He is called "Saint Justinian the Emperor" in the Eastern Orthodox Church. Because of his restoration activities, Justinian has sometimes been known as the "Last Roman" in mid-20th century historiography.\</item>
        <item>\St. Leo I, byname Leo the Great, pope from 440 to 461, master exponent of papal supremacy. His pontificate—which saw the disintegration of the Roman Empire in the West and the formation in the East of theological differences that were to split Christendom—was devoted to safeguarding orthodoxy and to securing the unity of the Western church under papal supremacy.\n\nConsecrated on September 29, 440, as successor to St. Sixtus III, Leo, one of the few popes termed great, immediately worked to suppress heresy, which he regarded as the cause of corruption and disunity. Yet his most significant theological achievement was not his negative suppression of heresy but his positive formulation of orthodoxy.\n\nHis treatment of the monk Eutyches of Constantinople provides an example. The monk had founded Eutychianism, an extreme form of monophysitism holding that Christ had only one nature, his human nature being absorbed in his divine nature. Patriarch Flavian of Constantinople excommunicated Eutyches, who then appealed to Leo. After examining the case, Leo sent Flavian (449) his celebrated Tome, which rejected Eutyches’ teaching and presented a precise, systematic doctrine of Christ’s Incarnation and of the union of both his natures. In 451 the Council of Chalcedon, summoned to condemn Eutychianism, declared that Leo’s Tome was the ultimate truth. Furthermore, the council recognized Leo’s doctrine as “the voice of Peter.” Thus for the church Leo’s Tome established the doctrine that Christ’s natures coexist and his Incarnation reveals how human nature is restored to perfect unity with divine, or absolute, being.\n\nLeo’s 432 letters and 96 sermons expound his precept of papal primacy in church jurisdiction. He held that papal power was granted by Christ to St. Peter alone, and that that power was passed on by Peter to his successors. In one letter, for example, he cautioned the Bishop of Thessalonica that although he had been entrusted with office and shared Leo’s solicitude, he was “not to possess the plenitude of power.”\n\nLeo further enhanced the prestige of the papacy and helped to place Western leadership in its hands by dealing with invading tribes. He persuaded the Huns, a nomadic people terrorizing northern Italy, not to attack Rome (452), and the Vandals, a Germanic people, not to sack Rome when they occupied it three years later. Leo was declared a doctor of the church by Pope Benedict XIV in 1754.\</item>

        <item>\Leonardo da Vinci was born on 15 April 1452 near the Tuscan town of Vinci, the illegitimate son of a local lawyer. He was apprenticed to the sculptor and painter Andrea del Verrocchio in Florence and in 1478 became an independent master. In about 1483, he moved to Milan to work for the ruling Sforza family as an engineer, sculptor, painter and architect. From 1495 to 1497 he produced a mural of \'The Last Supper\' in the refectory of the Monastery of Santa Maria delle Grazie, Milan.\n\nDa Vinci was in Milan until the city was invaded by the French in 1499 and the Sforza family forced to flee. He may have visited Venice before returning to Florence. During his time in Florence, he painted several portraits, but the only one that survives is the famous \'Mona Lisa\' (1503-1506).\n\nIn 1506, da Vinci returned to Milan, remaining there until 1513. This was followed by three years based in Rome. In 1517, at the invitation of the French king Francis I, Leonardo moved to the Château of Cloux, near Amboise in France, where he died on 2 May 1519.\n\nThe fame of Da Vinci\'s surviving paintings has meant that he has been regarded primarily as an artist, but the thousands of surviving pages of his notebooks reveal the most eclectic and brilliant of minds. He wrote and drew on subjects including geology, anatomy (which he studied in order to paint the human form more accurately), flight, gravity and optics, often flitting from subject to subject on a single page, and writing in left-handed mirror script. He \'invented\' the bicycle, airplane, helicopter, and parachute some 500 years ahead of their time.\n\nIf all this work had been published in an intelligible form, da Vinci\'s place as a pioneering scientist would have been beyond dispute. Yet his true genius was not as a scientist or an artist, but as a combination of the two: an \'artist-engineer\'. His painting was scientific, based on a deep understanding of the workings of the human body and the physics of light and shade. His science was expressed through art, and his drawings and diagrams show what he meant, and how he understood the world to work.\</item>
        <item>\Leonidas (540-480 BC), the legendary king of Sparta, and the Battle of Thermopylae is one of the most brilliant events of the ancient Greek history, a great act of courage and self-sacrifice. This man and the battle itself has inspired since then many artists, poets and film-makers that hymn the spirit of him and his Spartans.\n\nLittle is known about the life of Leonidas before the Battle of Thermopylae. Historians believe that he was born around 540 BC and the he was son of King Anaxandrias II of Sparta, a descendant of Hercules, according to the myth. Leonidas was married to Gorgo and had a son. He must have succeeded his half-brother to the throne at around 488 BC, till his death in 480 BC. His name meant either the son of a lion or like a lion.\n\nIn summer of 480 BC, Xerxes, the king of Persia, was attacking Greece with a big and well-equiped army. As he had already conquered northern Greece and he was coming to the south, the Greeks decided to unite and confront him in Thermopylae, a narrow passage in central Greece. Leonidas and his army, 300 soldiers, went off to Thermopylae to join the other Greek armies. The Greeks altogether were about 4,000 soldiers, while the Persian army consisted of 80,000 soldiers.\n\nXerxes waited for 4 days before he attacked, believing that the Greeks would surrender. When Xerxes sent his heralds to the Greeks, asking for their weapons, as a sign of submission, Leonidas said the historical phrase Come and get them!, declaring the beginning of the battle.\n\nThe first days, the Greeks were resisting, until a local man, Ephialtes, revealed to the Persians a secret passage to circle the Greeks and win the battle. Seeing that the Persian army were about to circle them, Leonidas asked the other Greeks to leave the battlefield. He proposed that he and his army would stay back to cover their escape, while the other Greeks would leave to protect the rest of Greece from a future Persian invasion.\n\nTherefore, Leonidas with his 300 Spartans and 700 Thespians, who refused to leave, stayed back to fight the huge Persian army. They were all killed in the battlefield, in this deathtrap, protecting theie homeland and their values. After all, it was disgraceful for a Spartan to return to Sparta beaten in war. A Spartan would either return from war as a winner, or he should not return at all.\n\nToday, a modern monument lies on the site of the battle in Thermopylae to remind of this courageous action, while the tomb of this legendary king lies in his homeland, Sparta.\</item>
        <item>\Marco Emilio Polo was a Venetian merchant, explorer, and writer who travelled through Asia along the Silk Road between 1271 and 1295. His travels are recorded in The Travels of Marco Polo (also known as Book of the Marvels of the World and Il Milione, c. 1300), a book that described to Europeans the then mysterious culture and inner workings of the Eastern world, including the wealth and great size of the Mongol Empire and China in the Yuan Dynasty, giving their first comprehensive look into China, Persia, India, Japan and other Asian cities and countries.\n\nBorn in Venice, Marco learned the mercantile trade from his father and his uncle, Niccolò and Maffeo, who travelled through Asia and met Kublai Khan. In 1269, they returned to Venice to meet Marco for the first time. The three of them embarked on an epic journey to Asia, exploring many places along the Silk Road until they reached Cathay. They were received by the royal court of Kublai Khan, who was impressed by Marco\'s intelligence and humility. Marco was appointed to serve as Khan\'s foreign emissary, and he was sent on many diplomatic missions throughout the empire and Southeast Asia, such as in present-day Burma, India, Indonesia, Sri Lanka and Vietnam. As part of this appointment, Marco also travelled extensively inside China, living in the emperor\'s lands for 17 years and seeing many things that had previously been unknown to Europeans.Around 1291, the Polos also offered to accompany the Mongol princess Kököchin to Persia; they arrived around 1293. After leaving the princess, they travelled overland to Constantinople and then to Venice, returning home after 24 years. At this time, Venice was at war with Genoa; Marco was captured and imprisoned by the Genoans after joining the war effort and dictated his stories to Rustichello da Pisa, a cellmate. He was released in 1299, became a wealthy merchant, married, and had three children. He died in 1324 and was buried in the church of San Lorenzo in Venice.\</item>
        <item>\Known for his philosophical interests, Marcus Aurelius was one of the most respected emperors in Roman history. He was born into a wealthy and politically prominent family. Growing up, Marcus Aurelius was a dedicated student, learning Latin and Greek. But his greatest intellectual interest was Stoicism, a philosophy that emphasized fate, reason, and self-restraint. Discourses, written by a former slave and Stoic philosopher Epictetus, had a great deal of influence over Marcus Aurelius.\n\nHis serious and hard-working nature was even noticed by Emperor Hadrian. After his earlier choice for a successor died, Hadrian adopted Titus Aurelius Antoninus (who would be known as Emperor Pius Antonius) to succeed him as an emperor. Hadrian also arranged for Antoninus to adopt Marcus Aurelius and the son of his earlier successor. Around the age of 17, Marcus Aurelius became the son of Antoninus. He worked alongside his adopted father while learning the ways of government and public affairs.\n\nIn 140, Marcus Aurelius became consul, or leader of the senate – a post he would hold two more times in his lifetime. As the years passed, he received more responsibilities and official powers, evolving into a strong source of support and counsel for Antoninus. Marcus Aurelius also continued his philosophical studies and developed an interest in law.\n\nAlong with his burgeoning career, Marcus Aurelius seemed to have a contented personal life. He married Faustina, the emperor’s daughter, in 145. Together they had many children, though some did not live for long. Best known are their daughter Lucilla and their son Commodus.\n\nAfter his adoptive father died in 161, Marcus Aurelius rose to power and was officially then known as Marcus Aurelius Antoninus Augustus. While some sources indicate that Antoninus selected him as his only successor, Marcus Aurelius insisted that his adopted brother served as his co-ruler. His brother was Lucius Aurelius Verus Augustus (usually referred to as Verus). Unlike the peaceful and prosperous rule of Antoninus, the joint reign of the two brothers was marked by war and disease. In the 160s, they battled with the Parthian empire for control over lands in the East. Verus oversaw the war effort while Marcus Aurelius stayed in Rome. Much of their success in this conflict has been attributed to the generals working under Verus, especially Avidius Cassius. He was later made governor of Syria. Returning soldiers brought some type of disease back with them to Rome, which lingered for years and wiped out a portion ofthe population. As the Parthian War ended, the two rulers had to face another military conflict with German tribes in the late 160s. German tribes crossed the Danube River and attacked a Roman city. After raising the necessary funds and troops, Marcus Aurelius and Verus went off to fight the invaders. Verus died in 169 so Marcus Aurelius pushed on alone, attempting to drive away the Germans.\n\nIn 175, he faced another challenge, this time for his very position. After hearing a rumor about Marcus Aurelius being deathly ill, Avidius Cassius claimed the title of emperor for himself. This forced Marcus Aurelius to travel to the East to regain control. But he did not have to fight Cassius as he was murdered by his own soldiers. Instead Marcus Aurelius toured eastern provinces with his wife, re-establishing his authority. Unfortunately, Faustina died during this trip.\n\nWhile once again battling the German tribes, Marcus Aurelius made his son Commodus his co-ruler in 177. Together they fought the northern enemies of the empire. Marcus Aurelius even hoped to extend the empire’s borders through this conflict, but Marcus Aurelius did not live long enough to see this vision to completion.Marcus Aurelius died on March 17, 180. His son Commodus became emperor and soon ended the northern military efforts. Marcus Aurelius, however, is not best remembered for the wars he waged, but for his contemplative nature and his rule driven by reason. A collection of his thoughts have been published in a work called The Meditations. Based on his Stoic beliefs, the work is filled with his notes on life.\</item>
        <item>\Mehmed II, called the Conqueror, was born in March 30, 1432 and died in May 3, 1481. As a sultan of the Ottoman Empire between 1444-1446 and 1451-1481, he extended the Ottoman control from southeastern Europe to the Danube and from Anatolia to the Euphrates river. His father, Murad II, tried to abdicate when Mehmet was only 12 years old, but in the wake of the son\'s unsuccessful first reign, the father returned to power.\n\nWhen the more mature Mehmet ascended the throne once more (after Murat\'s death), he tried to create a world empire like that of the Romans. He first conquered Constantinople in 1453 from the Byzantines and rebuilt it into the prosperous Ottoman capital of Istanbul. To counter the power of the Turkish aristocracy, Mehmet continued his father\'s policy of expanding the Janissary infantry corps. These Janissaries were made up of young Christians, recruited through the devshirme system, who were given salaries rather than fiefdoms to keep them loyal to and dependent on the sultan. Mehmet authorized autonomous religious communities to give his subjects religious freedom and gain the support of their religious leaders. Equitable tax and administrative systems were created, and justice for all was emphasized.\n\nMehmet subsequently conquered Serbia in 1459 and the Morea by 1460, extending the empire in Europe to the Danube and the Aegean despite resistance from Albania and Venice, with which he warred between 1463 and 1479. By 1461 he had conquered Anatolia as far as the Euphrates from the Turkmen principalities, but Mehmed failed to push further due to resistance from the Mamelukes of Syria as well as from the White Sheep Turkmen of Iran. He was just beginning new campaigns to capture Rhodes and southern Italy when he died suddenly in 1481. Mehmet II was succeeded by his son, Bayezid II.\</item>
        <item>\Napoleon Bonaparte was born on 15 August 1769 in Corsica into a gentry family. Educated at military school, he was rapidly promoted and in 1796, was made commander of the French army in Italy, where he forced Austria and its allies to make peace. In 1798, Napoleon conquered Ottoman-ruled Egypt in an attempt to strike at British trade routes with India. He was stranded when his fleet was destroyed by the British at the Battle of the Nile.\n\nFrance now faced a new coalition - Austria and Russia had allied with Britain. Napoleon returned to Paris where the government was in crisis. In a coup d\'etat in November 1799, Napoleon became first consul. In 1802, he was made consul for life and two years later, emperor. He oversaw the centralisation of government, the creation of the Bank of France, the reinstatement of Roman Catholicism as the state religion and law reform with the Code Napoleon.\n\nIn 1800, he defeated the Austrians at Marengo. He then negotiated a general European peace which established French power on the continent. In 1803, Britain resumed war with France, later joined by Russia and Austria. Britain inflicted a naval defeat on the French at Trafalgar (1805) so Napoleon abandoned plans to invade England and turned on the Austro-Russian forces, defeating them at Austerlitz later the same year. He gained much new territory, including annexation of Prussian lands which ostensibly gave him control of Europe. The Holy Roman Empire was dissolved, Holland and Westphalia created, and over the next five years, Napoleon\'s relatives and loyalists were installed as leaders (in Holland, Westphalia, Italy, Naples, Spain and Sweden).\n\nIn 1810, he had his childless marriage to Josephine de Beauharnais annulled and married the daughter of the Austrian emperor in the hope of having an heir. A son, Napoleon, was born a year later.\n\nThe Peninsular War began in 1808. Costly French defeats over the next five years drained French military resources. Napoleon\'s invasion of Russia in 1812 resulted in a disastrous retreat. The tide started to turn in favour of the allies and in March 1814, Paris fell. Napoleon went into exile on the Mediterranean island of Elba. In March 1815 he escaped and marched on the French capital. The Battle of Waterloo ended his brief second reign. The British imprisoned him on the remote Atlantic island of St Helena, where he died on 5 May 1821.\</item>
        <item>\Oliver Cromwell was born to Robert and Elizabeth Cromwell in Huntingdon, England, on January 30, 1599. The second born of 10 children, Oliver’s beginnings were humble and obscure, leading to the existence of minimal documentation on his early life. Cromwell gained a basic education from a Huntingdon grammar school that was joined to the Hospital of St. John, after which he attended Sidney Sussex College in Cambridge. During this time he earned a modest living off of the rents of the tenants of his owned land. His Father’s death in June of 1617 ended his time at the university, and he returned home to care for his sisters and mother, as well as govern his family’s estate. \n\n Cromwell married Elizabeth Bourchier, the daughter of London merchant Sir James Bourchier, in August of 1620.\n\n Cromwell was elected as a Member of Parliament for Huntingdon in 1628, and rapidly became viewed as no friend of King Charles. Cromwell, after his first service to parliament, fell into depression, and suffered from some unknown illness, which resulted in him having a, “spiritual awakening”, which resulted in an extreme and uncompromising Puritan belief system. With his income and fortunes dropping rapidly, he sold a fair portion of his land in and around Huntingdon, and prompted him and his family to move to the Cambridge town of St. Ives in 1631, where he became a farmer on leased land. Cromwell worked here in such a manner for five years when his maternal, and heirless, uncle died, leaving Oliver a large inheritance in another Cambridge town, Ely, in 1636. With his improvement in hierarchical society, Cromwell was elected to Parliament twice in 1640. Cromwell did not become a nationally recognized political and military leader until the mid-1640s.\n\n The First English Civil War began in August 1642, and Oliver Cromwell joined the war effort of the parliamentary army, leading an early military engagement in the conflict. He compiled a small force of horsemen, secured Cambridge for Parliamentary forces, and then joined the Earl of Sussex at the Battle of Edgehill. Cromwell distinguished himself in battles around Gainsborough in July of 1643. He was then given the rank of Colonel in the Eastern Association army, and made governor of Ely. In 1644 he became a Lieutenant General in the Eastern Association Cavalry, and was instrumental in a Parliament victory at Marston Moor, where his actions earned him the nickname “Ironside”. 1645 saw him placed under Sir Thomas Fairfax as second in command of the new army, and deciding the outcome of the battle of Naseby, which effectively ended the first Civil War.\n\n In 1648, the second English Civil War commenced, and Cromwell returned to the battlefield. He began a campaign by ending an uprising of Royalists in South Wales, and then annihilated the Scottish Army at the battle of Preston. After his campaign in the North, Cromwell returned to London and he, along with 58 others, signed the orders for the execution of King Charles.\n\n After the King’s execution, a Council of State was instituted in place of a monarchy. This council ordered Cromwell to take Ireland in 1649, followed by Scotland in 1650. His actions led to his appointment to Lord General, the high commander of the parliamentary military. Cromwell led his armies into battle at Worcester, in September of 1651, and the resulting victory united England, Scotland, and Ireland, into the Commonwealth.\n\nDecember of 1653 saw Cromwell appointed Lord Protector, the administrator of government and chief magistrate of the Commonwealth. He was offered the crown at one point by parliament, but declined the offer. A constitution decreed that if he wished to call or dissolve a parliament, he must receive a majority vote from the Council of State. This check on power led to the ruling that a monarch of England, without parliament’s approval, cannot govern.\n\n After serving as the Lord Protector of England for five years, Oliver Cromwell died as a result of a urinary infection on September 3, 1658. He was buried in Westminster Abbey.\n\n In 1660, after the protectorate was overthrown due to lack of leadership, an English monarchy was reestablished with Charles II being named King. In 1661, Cromwell’s body was exhumed from Westminster, tried for treason, and executed, despite already being dead. The corpse was beheaded, and the head was displayed upon spikes atop Westminster hall.\</item>
        <item>\Otto Eduard Leopold von Bismarck was born into an aristocratic family at Schönhausen, northwest of Berlin, on 1 April 1815. He attended a prestigious school in Berlin followed by the University of Göttingen. He then entered the Prussian civil service but was bored by his job and in 1838 resigned. For nearly a decade, he helped his father manage the family estates.\n\nIn 1847, Bismarck married Johanna von Puttkamer, who provided him with stability. It was a year of significant change in his life, when he also embraced the Christian tradition of Lutheranism, and began his political career in the Prussian legislature, where he gained a reputation as an ultra-conservative royalist. In 1851, King Frederick Wilhelm IV appointed Bismarck as Prussian representative to the German Confederation. He then served as ambassador to Russia and France. In 1862, he returned to Prussia and was appointed prime minister by the new king, Wilhelm I.\n\nBismarck was now determined to unite the German states into a single empire, with Prussia at its core. With Austrian support, he used the expanded Prussian army to capture the provinces of Schleswig and Holstein from Denmark. He then escalated a quarrel with Austria and its German allies over the administration of these provinces into a war, in which Prussia was the victor. Prussia then annexed further territory in Germany.\n\nUnable to persuade the southern German states to join with his North German Confederation, he provoked hostilities with France as a way of uniting the German states together. The German victory in the Franco-Prussian War won over the southern German states, and in 1871 they agreed to join a German empire. Wilhelm I of Prussia became emperor.\n\nAs \'chancellor\' of the new Germany, Bismarck concentrated on building a powerful state with a unified national identity. One of his targets was the Catholic Church, which he believed had too much influence, particularly in southern Germany. He also worked to prevent the spread of socialism, partly by introducing health insurance and pensions.\n\nAbroad, Bismarck aimed to make the German empire the most powerful in Europe. In 1879, he negotiated an alliance with Austria-Hungary to counteract France and Russia. Italy later joined the alliance. To avoid alienating Britain, Bismarck arranged the two Mediterranean Agreements of 1887, designed to preserve the status quo against a Russian threat.\n\nIn 1890, Bismarck resigned after disagreeing with the new emperor, Wilhelm II. He retired to his estate near Hamburg and died there on 30 July 1898.\</item>
        <item>\Peter the Great  Peter I or Pyotr Alekséyevich was a monarch of the Tsardom of Russia and later the Russian Empire from 7 May [O.S. 27 April] 1682 until his death in 1725, jointly ruling before 1696 with his elder half-brother, Ivan V. Under his reign, Russia was modernised and grew into a European power.\n\nThrough a number of successful wars, he captured ports at Azov and the Baltic Sea, laying the groundwork for the Imperial Russian Navy, ending uncontested Swedish supremacy in the Baltic and beginning the Tsardom\'s expansion into a much larger empire that became a major European power. He led a cultural revolution that replaced some of the traditionalist and medieval social and political systems with ones that were modern, scientific, Westernised and based on the Enlightenment. Peter\'s reforms had a lasting impact on Russia, and many institutions of the Russian government trace their origins to his reign. He adopted the title of Emperor in place of the old title of Tsar in 1721, and founded and developed the city of Saint Petersburg, which remained the capital of Russia until 1917.\</item>
        <item>\Richard was born on 8 September 1157 in Oxford, son of Henry II and Eleanor of Aquitaine. He possessed considerable political and military ability. However, like his brothers, he fought with his family, joining them in the great rebellion against their father in 1173. In 1183 his brother Henry died, leaving Richard heir to the throne. Henry II wanted to give Aquitaine to his youngest son, John. Richard refused and, in 1189, joined forces with Philip II of France against his father, hounding him to a premature death in July 1189.\n\nAs king, Richard\'s chief ambition was to join the Third Crusade, prompted by Saladin\'s capture of Jerusalem in 1187. To finance this, he sold sheriffdoms and other offices and in 1190 he departed for the Holy Land. In May, he reached Cyprus where he married Berengaria, daughter of the king of Navarre. Richard arrived in the Holy Land in June 1191 and Acre fell the following month. In September, his victory at Arsuf gave the crusaders possession of Joppa. Although he came close, Jerusalem, the crusade\'s main objective, eluded him. Moreover, fierce quarrels among the French, German and English contingents provided further troubles. After a year\'s stalemate, Richard made a truce with Saladin and started his journey home.\n\nBad weather drove him ashore near Venice and he was imprisoned by Duke Leopold of Austria before being handed over to the German emperor Henry VI, who ransomed him for the huge sum of 150,000 marks. The raising of the ransom was a remarkable achievement. In February 1194, Richard was released. He returned at once to England and was crowned for a second time, fearing that the ransom payment had compromised his independence. Yet a month later he went to Normandy, never to return. His last five years were spent in intermittent warfare against Philip II. While besieging the castle of Châlus in central France he was fatally wounded and died on 6 April 1199. He was succeeded by his younger brother John, who had spent the years of Richard\'s absence scheming against him.
\</item>

        <item>\Robert was born on 11 July 1274 into an aristocratic Scottish family. Through his father he was distantly related to the Scottish royal family. His mother had Gaelic antecedents. Bruce\'s grandfather was one of the claimants to the Scottish throne during a succession dispute in 1290 - 1292. The English king, Edward I, was asked to arbitrate and chose John Balliol to be king. Both Bruce and his father refused to back Balliol and supported Edward I\'s invasion of Scotland in 1296 to force Balliol to abdicate. Edward then ruled Scotland as a province of England.\n\nBruce then supported William Wallace\'s uprising against the English. After Wallace was defeated, Bruce\'s lands were not confiscated and in 1298, Bruce became a guardian of Scotland, with John Comyn, Balliol\'s nephew and Bruce\'s greatest rival for the Scottish throne In 1306, Bruce quarrelled with Comyn and stabbed him in a church in Dumfries. He was outlawed by Edward and excommunicated by the pope. Bruce now proclaimed his right to the throne and on 27 March was crowned king at Scone. The following year, Bruce was deposed by Edward\'s army and forced to flee. His wife and daughters were imprisoned and three of his brothers executed. Robert spent the winter on the island off the coast of Antrim (Northern Ireland).\n\nReturning to Scotland, Robert waged a highly successful guerrilla war against the English. At the Battle of Bannockburn in June 1314, he defeated a much larger English army under Edward II, confirming the re-establishment of an independent Scottish monarchy. Two years later, his brother Edward Bruce was inaugurated as high king of Ireland but was killed in battle in 1318. Even after Bannockburn and the Scottish capture of Berwick in 1318, Edward II refused to give up his claim to the overlordship of Scotland. In 1320, the Scottish earls, barons and the \'community of the realm\' sent a letter to Pope John XXII declaring that Robert was their rightful monarch. This was the \'Declaration of Arbroath\' and it asserted the antiquity of the Scottish people and their monarchy.\n\nFour years later, Robert received papal recognition as king of an independent Scotland. The Franco-Scottish alliance was renewed in the Treaty of Corbeil, by which the Scots were obliged to make war on England should hostilities break out between England and France. In 1327, the English deposed Edward II in favour of his son and peace was made with Scotland. This included a total renunciation of all English claims to superiority over Scotland. Robert died on 7 June 1329. He was buried at Dunfermline. He requested that his heart be taken to the Holy Land, but it only got as far as Spain. It was returned to Scotland and buried in Melrose Abbey.\</item>
        <item>\Saladin is the Western name of Salah al-Din Yusuf ibn Ayyub, the Muslim sultan of Egypt and Syria who famously defeated a massive army of Crusaders in the Battle of Hattin and captured the city of Jerusalem in 1187. At the height of his power, he ruled a unified Muslim region stretching from Egypt to Arabia. Saladin was celebrated by Muslims and many Westerners of later generations for his political and military skills, as well as his generosity and chivalry.\n\nSaladin was born Yusuf Ibn Ayyub in the central Iraqi city of Tikrit in 1137 or 1138. His family was of Kurdish descent, and his father Ayyub and uncle Shirkuh were elite military leaders under Imad al-Din Zangi, a powerful ruler who governed northern Syria at the time. After growing up in Damascus and rising through the military ranks, the young Saladin joined an army commanded by his uncle Shirkuh, who served Zangi’s son and heir, Nur al-Din, on a military expedition to Egypt.\n\nIn 1169, after Shirkuh’s death, Saladin was chosen to succeed him in command of Nur al-Din’s forces in Egypt. He was also appointed vizier of the crumbling Fatimid Caliphate, which ruled Egypt at the time. With the death of the last Fatimid caliph in 1171, Saladin became governor of Egypt, and set about reducing the power and influence of Shia Islam and reestablishing a Sunni regime there. Governing in the name of Nur al-Din, he strengthened Egypt as a base of Sunni power in the Near East.\n\nNur al-Din died in 1174, and Saladin launched a campaign to take control of the lands he had ruled. He also sought to establish his regime as a major military player capable of challenging the four Western-controlled Crusader states, which had been established after the First Crusade in 1098-99.\n\nAs sultan of Egypt, Saladin returned to Syria and managed to capture Damascus, Aleppo, and Mosul from other Muslim rulers. Saladin’s forces also conquered Yemen, which enabled him to consolidate control over the entire Red Sea. In addition to his military exploits, he also pursued diplomatic efforts to achieve his goals. He married Nur ad-Din\'s widow, Ismat, who was also the daughter of the late Damascan ruler Unur, which helped him gain legitimacy through association with two ruling dynasties. Finally, he gained widespread Muslim support by proclaiming himself the leader of a jihad, or holy war, dedicated to defending Islam against Christianity.\n\nSaladin’s goal was to unite the Muslim territories of Syria, northern Mesopotamia, Palestine and Egypt under his rule, and by 1186 he had achieved it through a mix of diplomacy and military force. Known for his love of poetry and gardens, he also gained a reputation as a generous and noble leader—helped along by the official biographers he hired to record his feats.\n\nAfter nearly a decade of fighting smaller battles against the Franks (as the Crusaders from Western Europe were called), Saladin prepared to launch a full-scale attack in 1187 by assembling troops from across his realm south of Damascus and an impressive Egyptian fleet at Alexandria. His army met the Franks in a massive clash at Hattin, near Tiberias (modern-day Israel) and defeated them soundly on July 4, 1187.\n\nVictory in the Battle of Hattin was followed by a string of quick victories across the Kingdom of Jerusalem, culminating on October 2, 1187, when the City of Jerusalem surrendered to Saladin’s army after 88 years under Christian control. Though Saladin had planned to kill all Christians in Jerusalem as revenge for the slaughter of Muslims in 1099, he agreed to let them purchase their freedom instead.\n\nBy that time, Saladin’s forces had taken control of a number of other important cities from the Crusaders, including Acre, Tiberias, Caesarea, Nazareth and Jaffa. Yet he didn’t manage to capture Tyre, the coastal fortress to which most of the surviving Crusaders retreated after their defeats.\n\nIn the wake of Saladin’s capture of Jerusalem, Pope Gregory III called for a new Crusade to recapture the city. In 1189, Christian forces mobilized at Tyre to launch the Third Crusade, led by three powerful kings: Frederick I “Barbarossa,” the German king and Holy Roman Emperor, King Philip II of France and Richard I “the Lionheart” of England.\n\nThe Crusaders laid siege to Acre, finally capturing it in 1191 along with a large part of Saladin’s navy. Yet despite the military prowess of the Crusader forces, Saladin withstood their onslaught and managed to retain control over most of his empire. His truce with Richard the Lionheart in late 1192 ended the Third Crusade.\n\nJust a few months later, in March 1193, Saladin died in his beloved gardens in Damascus. Though relatively young (just 55 or 56), he was exhausted from a life spent in near continuous military campaigns. By the time of his death, he had given away much of his personal wealth to his subjects, leaving behind not even enough to pay for his own burial. The coalition of Muslim states Saladin assembled would pull apart after his death, but his descendants in the Ayyubid dynasty continued to rule in Egypt and Syria for several generations.\</item>
        <item>\Suleiman was born in Trabzon (today part of Turkey) in 1494. His father, Selim I, was the Sultan (like an emperor) of the Ottoman Empire. Suleiman grew up in the beautiful Topkapi Palace in Istanbul, the capital city of the Ottoman Empire. He attended school and was taught by some of the top Islamic scholars of the time. He studied a variety of subjects including history, science, military strategy, and literature.\n\nSuleiman\'s early career helped to prepare him for the day he would become Sultan. While still a teenager, he was appointed governor of Kaffa. As governor, he learned how politics and the law worked. He also learned about different cultures and places in the empire. In 1520, Suleiman\'s father died and Suleiman became the new Sultan of the Ottoman Empire at the age of 26.\n\nUpon assuming the throne, Suleiman didn\'t waste any time. He immediately began military campaigns to expand his empire. He dreamt of a united empire that stretched from Europe to India.\n\nSuleiman carried out several military campaigns during his 46 year rule. He moved into central Europe taking over parts of Hungary and Romania. He also built up a powerful navy and took control of the Mediterranean Sea. In the Middle East, he defeated the Safavids, uniting a large part of the Islamic world. He also conquered many lands and cities in northern Africa.\n\nAs Suleiman surged into Hungary, he struck fear in the hearts of many in Europe. One of the main powers of Europe was the Habsburg Empire of Austria. They also were leaders of the Holy Roman Empire. Their capital city was Vienna. In 1529, Suleiman and his army arrived at Vienna.\n\nSuleiman\'s army laid siege to Vienna for over two weeks. However, the march to Vienna had taken its toll on his army. Many of his soldiers were sick and he had to abandon his siege equipment along the way due to bad weather. When winter snows arrived early, Suleiman had to turn back, suffering his first major defeat at the hands of the Europeans.\n\nSuleiman\'s accomplishments while ruling as the Ottoman Sultan were by no means limited to his military expansion. He was an excellent leader and helped to transform the Ottoman Empire into an economic powerhouse. He reformed the law and created a single legal code. He also reworked the tax system, built schools, and supported the arts. The time period of Sulieman\'s rule is known as a golden age in the culture of the Ottoman Empire.\n\nSuleiman became sick and died while on campaign in Hungary on September 7, 1566.\</item>
        <item>\Tancred of Hauteville, French Tancrède de Hauteville, regent of Antioch, one of the leaders of the First Crusade.\n\nTancred was a Norman lord of south Italy. He went on the Crusade with his uncle, Bohemond (the future Bohemond I of Antioch), and first distinguished himself in Cilicia, where he captured Tarsus from the Turks and came into conflict with his fellow Crusader, Baldwin of Boulogne. He played a prominent part in most of the major battles of the Crusade, and after the capture of Jerusalem (1099) he received the title Prince of Galilee. He served as regent of the principality of Antioch for Bohemond while the latter was a prisoner of the Turks (1101–03) and controlled Antioch permanently after Bohemond returned to Europe in 1104.\n\nAs regent of Antioch, and also of Edessa from 1104 to 1108, Tancred became the chief Latin magnate of northern Syria, engaging in continual warfare with both the Turks and the Byzantines until his death.\</item>
        <item>\Theodora, Byzantine empress, wife of the emperor Justinian I (reigned 527–565), probably the most powerful woman in Byzantine history. Her intelligence and political acumen made her Justinian’s most trusted adviser and enabled her to use the power and influence of her office to promote religious and social policies that favoured her interests.\n\nLittle is known of Theodora’s early life, but a combination of the official version with that found in the highly coloured Secret History of Procopius of Caesarea probably provides the best explanation. Her father, Acacius, was a bear keeper at the Hippodrome in Constantinople. Procopius says that she became an actress and prostitute while still young, leading an unconventional life that included giving birth to at least one child out of wedlock. For a time, she made her living as a wool spinner. When Justinian met her, she had been converted to miaphysitism, a nonorthodox doctrine. Attracted by her beauty and intelligence, he made her his mistress and married her in 525. Her disreputable background meant that prior to the marriage, special legislation had to be passed legalizing unions between actresses and men of senatorial rank or higher. When Justinian succeeded to the throne in 527, she was proclaimed augusta.\n\nTheodora exercised considerable influence, and though she was never coregent, her superior intelligence and deft handling of political affairs caused many to think that it was she, rather than Justinian, who ruled Byzantium. Her name is mentioned in nearly all the laws passed during that period. She received foreign envoys and corresponded with foreign rulers, functions usually reserved for the emperor. Her influence in political affairs was decisive, as illustrated in the Nika revolt of January 532. The two political factions in Constantinople, the Blues and the Greens, united in their opposition to the government and set up a rival emperor. Justinian’s advisers urged him to flee, but Theodora advised him to stay and save his empire, whereupon Justinian’s general, Belisarius, herded the rioters into the Hippodrome and cut them to pieces.\n\nTheodora is remembered as one of the first rulers to recognize the rights of women, passing strict laws to prohibit the traffic in young girls and altering the divorce laws to give greater benefits to women. She spent much of her reign trying to mitigate the laws against the miaphysites. Though she succeeded in ending their persecution in 533, she never succeeded in changing Justinian’s religious policy from its emphasis on orthodoxy and friendship with Rome.\n\nThe best-known representation of Theodora is the mosaic portrait in the church of San Vitale in Ravenna, Italy. Her death, possibly from cancer or gangrene, was a severe blow to Justinian. Her importance in Byzantine political life is shown by the fact that little significant legislation dates from the period between her death and that of Justinian (565).\</item>
        <item>\Trajan was a Roman emperor who ruled from A.D. 98 until his death in A.D. 117. Born in Italica (Seville in modern-day Spain), Trajan was the first Roman emperor born outside of Italy. He was also one of the first emperors to be chosen, rather than to inherit power as part of a ruling family.\n\nBefore he was emperor, Trajan was an army commander, senator, and governor of upper Germany. These experiences helped him gain the support of both the sitting emperor, Nerva, who named him as his successor, and generals of the Roman army.\n\nAfter Nerva’s death in A.D. 98, Trajan prioritized protecting and expanding the Roman Empire. He twice defeated the people from the region of Dacia, where modern-day Romania is located. He used the bountiful plunder from these victories to fund public works projects in Rome. These included a spacious new forum with two libraries and a massive stone column called Trajan’s Column. The column was covered in carvings depicting the victory over the Dacians and still stands today. It is one of the largest monuments to survive the fall of Rome.\n\nDuring his 19-year reign, Trajan expanded the Roman Empire to its farthest territorial limits up until that date. The empire stretched from Scotland down to Northern Africa and swept east across the Mediterranean as far as Mesopotamia, or modern-day Iraq.\n\nTrajan ruled strictly, but fairly, and struck an effective balance between making conquests and maintaining a high quality of life for his people. Trajan died in A.D. 117 after falling ill while defending the empire’s extensive borders.\</item>
        <item>\Vlad the Impaler, in full Vlad III Dracula or Romanian Vlad III Drăculea, also called Vlad III or Romanian Vlad Țepeș, (born 1431, Sighișoara, Transylvania — died 1476, north of present-day Bucharest, Romania), voivode (military governor, or prince) of Walachia (1448; 1456–1462; 1476) whose cruel methods of punishing his enemies gained notoriety in 15th-century Europe. Some in the scholarly community have suggested that Bram Stoker’s Dracula character was based on Vlad.\n\nVlad was the second of four brothers born into the noble family of Vlad II Dracul. His sobriquet Dracula (meaning “son of Dracul”) was derived from the Latin draco (“dragon”) after his father’s induction into the Order of the Dragon, created by Holy Roman Emperor Sigismund for the defense of Christian Europe against the Ottoman Empire. Vlad moved to Târgoviște, Walachia, in 1436 when his father assumed leadership of the Walachian voivodate (principality). In 1442 Vlad and his younger brother were sent to the court of Ottoman Sultan Murad II as collateral to assure the sultan that their father, in a reversal of his previous position, would support Ottoman policies. Vlad returned in 1448, having been informed of the assassination of his father and elder brother at the hands of Walachian boyars (nobles) the year before.\n\nVlad then embarked upon the first of a lifelong series of campaigns to regain his father’s seat. His opponents included the boyars as well as his younger brother, who was supported by the Ottoman sultan. He emerged briefly victorious in 1448 but was deposed after only two months. After an eight-year struggle, Vlad again claimed the voivodate.\n\nIt was during this period of rule that he committed the atrocities for which he was best known. His penchant for impaling his enemies on stakes in the ground and leaving them to die earned him the name Vlad the Impaler (Romanian: Vlad Țepeș). He inflicted this type of torture on foreign and domestic enemies alike: notably, as he retreated from a battle in 1462, he left a field filled with thousands of impaled victims as a deterrent to pursuing Ottoman forces. That year he escaped Ottoman capture only to be intercepted by Hungarian forces and imprisoned by Matthias I of Hungary, whose assistance he had sought. Vlad regained his seat in 1476 but was killed in battle the same year. He remained a folk hero in the region for his efforts against Ottoman encroachment.\</item>
        <item>\William Wallace was born in the 1270s in Elderslie in Renfrewshire into a gentry family. Very little is known about his early years and there are significant periods of his life for which there are no reliable sources.\n\nIn 1296, Edward I of England had taken advantage of a succession crisis in Scotland and imposed himself as ruler with an English administration. Within months, Scottish unrest was widespread.\n\nIn May 1297, Wallace attacked the town of Lanark, killing the English sheriff and unrest quickly became full-blown rebellion. Men flocked to join Wallace and he began to drive the English out of Fife and Perthshire. In September 1297, Wallace defeated a much larger English force at the Battle of Stirling Bridge. This and subsequent military successes severely weakened the English hold on Scotland. Wallace then launched raids into England. In late 1297 or early 1298 he was knighted and appointed \'guardian of the kingdom\' in the name of John Balliol, the deposed king of Scotland.\n\nThe shock of the defeat at Stirling rallied the English around Edward, who marched north with an army. Wallace\'s strategy was to avoid confrontation and gradually withdraw. He destroyed the countryside as he went, forcing Edward to march deeper and deeper into Scotland. In July 1298, the Scottish and English armies met near Falkirk, and the Scots were defeated. Wallace escaped and little is known of his movements, but at some stage he resigned the guardianship and was succeeded by Robert Bruce and John Comyn.\n\nWallace then went abroad, notably to France, to seek support for the Scottish cause. He returned to Scotland in 1303. In his absence Robert Bruce had accepted a truce with Edward I and, in 1304, John Comyn came to terms with the English as well. Wallace was excluded from these terms and the English king offered a large sum of money to anyone who killed or captured him. Wallace was seized in or near Glasgow in August 1305, and transported to London. He was charged and tried with treason, which he denied, saying he had never sworn allegiance to the English king. His execution was held on 23 August, where he was hung, drawn and quartered. His head was placed on London Bridge, and his limbs displayed in Newcastle, Berwick, Stirling and Perth.\</item>
        <item>\Zenobia, in full Septimia Zenobia, Aramaic Znwbyā Bat Zabbai, (died after 274), queen of the Roman colony of Palmyra, in present-day Syria, from 267 or 268 to 272. She conquered several of Rome’s eastern provinces before she was subjugated by the emperor Aurelian (ruled 270–275).\n\nZenobia’s husband, Odaenathus, Rome’s client ruler of Palmyra, had by 267 recovered the Roman East from Persian conquerors. After Odaenathus and his eldest son (by his former wife), Herodes (or Herodianus), were assassinated in 267 or 268, Zenobia became regent for her own young son Wahballat (called Vaballathus in Latin, Athenodorus in Greek). Styling herself queen of Palmyra, she had Vaballathus adopt his father’s titles of “king of kings” and corrector totius Orientis (“governor of all the East”).\n\nNevertheless, unlike Odaenathus, Zenobia was not content to remain a Roman client. In 269 she seized Egypt, then conquered much of Asia Minor and declared her independence from Rome. Marching east, Aurelian defeated her armies at Antioch and at Emesa and besieged Palmyra. Zenobia and Vaballathus tried to flee from the city, but they were captured before they could cross the Euphrates River, and the Palmyrenes soon surrendered. When they revolted again in 273, the Romans recaptured and destroyed the city. Sources differ about Zenobia’s fate after her capture. According to some, Zenobia and Vaballathus graced the triumphal procession that Aurelian celebrated at Rome in 274. However, other historians claim that she starved herself to death during the trip to Rome.\</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="music_title">

        <item>Ode to Joy</item>
        <item>Song for the Morning Star</item>
        <item>Epitaph of Seikilos</item>
        <item>Fifth Symphony</item>
        <item>Silent Night</item>
        <item>Moonlight Sonata</item>
        <item>1812 Overture</item>
        <item>Magnum Mysterium</item>
        <item>Salve Regina</item>
        <item>Young Person\'s Guide to the Orchestra</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="music_composer">

        <item>Beethoven</item>
        <item>R. Carlos Nakai</item>
        <item>Unknown Greek Man</item>
        <item>Beethoven</item>
        <item>Franz Xaver Gruber and Joseph Mohr</item>
        <item>Beethoven</item>
        <item>Pyotr Ilyich Tchaikovsky</item>
        <item>Giovanni Pierluigi da Palestrina</item>
        <item>Jacob Obrecht</item>
        <item>Benjamin Britten</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="music_details">

        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>
        <item>Blank</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="art_name">

        <item>Saint George Killing the Dragon</item>
        <item>Wanderer Above a Sea of Fog</item>
        <item>The Scream</item>
        <item> Washington Crossing the Delaware</item>
        <item>La Liberté guidant le Peuple</item>
        <item>El Dos de Mayo de 1808 en Madrid</item>
        <item>American Gothic</item>
        <item>Last Supper</item>
        <item>Meisje met de parel</item>
        <item>The Swing</item>
        <item>The Great Wave off Kanagawa</item>
        <item>Mona Lisa</item>
        <item>God Creating Adam</item>
        <item>The Nightwatch</item>
        <item>Nascita di Venere</item>
        <item>Starry Night</item>

    </string-array>

    <string-array name="artist">

        <item>Bernardo Martorell</item>
        <item>Caspar David Friedrich</item>
        <item>Edvard Munch</item>
        <item>Emanuel Leutze</item>
        <item>Eugène Delacroix</item>
        <item>Francisco Goya</item>
        <item>Grant Wood</item>
        <item>Jacopo Tintoretto </item>
        <item>Jan Vermeer</item>
        <item>Jean-Honoré Fragonard</item>
        <item>Katsushika Hokusai</item>
        <item>Leonardo da Vinci</item>
        <item>Michelangelo Buonarroti</item>
        <item>Rembrandt van Rijn</item>
        <item>Sandro Boticelli</item>
        <item>Vincent van Gogh</item>

    </string-array>

</resources>